<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cause of God, and of these nations sought out, and drawn forth from the rubbish of the lusts and interests of men, and lifted up into sight and view for all the upright in heart to follow it. Wherein is shewed, what our cause was. What opportunity we had for it. How miserably it has been deserted. What was the cause of that desertion. The spiritual judgment that is already upon the desertors. With a word of encouragement to all the faithful, and persevering friends of it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E968_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866739</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74960)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 144:E968[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cause of God, and of these nations sought out, and drawn forth from the rubbish of the lusts and interests of men, and lifted up into sight and view for all the upright in heart to follow it. Wherein is shewed, what our cause was. What opportunity we had for it. How miserably it has been deserted. What was the cause of that desertion. The spiritual judgment that is already upon the desertors. With a word of encouragement to all the faithful, and persevering friends of it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 33 [i.e. 34], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed anno Dom. 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "what our cause was ... upon the desertors." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>P. 34 misnumbered 33.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march. 2:d march 2. 1658"; the 9 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with an "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAUSE of GOD, And of theſe NATIONS. Sought out, and drawn forth from the Rubbiſh of the Luſts and Intereſts of Men, and lifted up into ſight and view for all the upright in heart to follow it. Wherein is ſhewed,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>What our Cauſe was.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>What opportunity we had for it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>How miſerably it has been deſerted.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>What was the Cauſe of that deſertion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſpiritual Judgment that is already upon the Deſertors.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> With a Word of encouragement to all the faithful, and perſevering friends of it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 59.19</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When the Enemy ſhall come in like a flood, the Spirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a Standard againſt him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:2"/>
            <head>To all the Honeſt-hearted of the Land; who though through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they have ſtaggered, yet have not wickedly departed from the Cauſe of God and the Nation.</head>
            <p>GOD hath <hi>pardoned</hi> your ſins, You have had your <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> and <hi>weakneſſes,</hi> and God hath <hi>chastend</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted</hi> you for them; You have <hi>borne</hi> your <hi>ſhame,</hi> you have <hi>turned away</hi> from <hi>God</hi> &amp; <hi>rejoyced</hi> in a thing of <hi>nought:</hi> Therefore God hath <hi>withdrawn</hi> from you his <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>bleſſing,</hi> and your <hi>Renown</hi> is much <hi>periſhed.</hi> You have minded the <hi>enriching</hi> of your ſelves, the making your <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Names</hi> Great: Therefore hath God ſet up a <hi>greatneſs</hi> over you to <hi>afflict</hi> you. You would be ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> and ſo in the <hi>faſhion</hi> of the World, and of the <hi>Nations,</hi> ſo afraid of the <hi>meanneſs</hi> of Chriſt and of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that I think ye have had enough of a <hi>Lordly</hi> Spirit; and yet in the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> too, bringing you under. God hath <hi>payd</hi> you in your <hi>own Coine.</hi> Ye would ride upon <hi>horſes,</hi> and upon the <hi>ſwift,</hi> therefore they that have <hi>purſued</hi> you have been <hi>ſwift.</hi> Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God in his <hi>Judgements,</hi> Confeſſe him and ſanctifie his Name.</p>
            <p>Are ye <hi>willing</hi> to be <hi>delivered?</hi> Or do ye affect <hi>bondage</hi> ſtill? Will ye be <hi>boared</hi> for perpetual ſlaves? Will ye yet <hi>accept</hi> of the Government of Chriſt? Are ye <hi>weary and heavy laden?</hi> Will ye put into a good <hi>harbour?</hi> The Lord opens his Arms to you, He
<pb facs="tcp:119024:3"/>
               <hi>waits that he may be gracious.</hi> He hath hid <hi>love</hi> under all this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation; Theſe <hi>winds</hi> and <hi>waves</hi> have been but to waft you over into his <hi>own Boſome.</hi> It is one of his Ordinances, <hi>In the world you ſhall have tribulation.</hi> But <hi>he is</hi> wherever he <hi>was,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is, and <hi>lives;</hi> All ye that are the <hi>Natural</hi> children of it, Come own your <hi>Mother. Jeruſalem</hi> which is <hi>above is free, which is the Mother of us all,</hi> and ye are free, and nothing can inthral you, no <hi>Bonds,</hi> no <hi>Yokes,</hi> no <hi>Temptations,</hi> no <hi>allurements</hi> can hold you in that that is <hi>unrighteous.</hi> Ye can not <hi>rest</hi> till ye come to your own <hi>Land,</hi> till ye ſee the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> dwells. Of whatſoever <hi>Kindred, Nation, Tribe,</hi> or <hi>Tongue</hi> ye are, no Form can or ſhall impriſon you long, or hold the <hi>truth in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> I know ye have your <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Lights,</hi> and diſcernings <hi>gradually</hi> differing; But ye are <hi>one,</hi> and agree <hi>perfectly</hi> in the true <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of your life. Ye would have <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> take place, that is, Ye would have <hi>Christ reign.</hi> For <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> are but ſo many <hi>Names</hi> of <hi>Him;</hi> and he would have ye happy and <hi>free</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, free in your <hi>Perſons,</hi> free in your <hi>Estates,</hi> free <hi>inwardly,</hi> free <hi>outwardly:</hi> for the <hi>Earth</hi> is his as well as <hi>Heaven,</hi> He made it, and that not in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ain,</hi> He made it to be <hi>inhabited,</hi> Sin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs hath <hi>deſolated</hi> it. The fruit of the <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and comely, when the Branch of the Lord is beautiful and glorious for his eſcaped Remnant. He hath married you and calls you by <hi>Name:</hi> You are the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> race, thoſe that are againſt you are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> and forreigners, <hi>Aliens</hi> from their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; Therefore when I call you <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> it is as much as if I call'd you <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye are but a <hi>Remnant,</hi> yet ye are the <hi>ſeed</hi> and <hi>hopes</hi> of the Land; God hath <hi>winnowed</hi> and ſifted the Nation; thoſe that were not of you, are fallen off from you. It is your advantage that you <hi>know</hi> them, you ſhall not <hi>want</hi> their <hi>Numbers,</hi> nor need you <hi>fear</hi> their <hi>Multitude;</hi> for the whole Multitudes that gather againſt you, ſhall be as <hi>the Dream of a night Viſion.</hi> God is ariſen to <hi>judge</hi> them, ye ſhall need to do nothing againſt them, but to ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:3"/>
            <p>Their Mighty men are fallen, their ſtrength is periſhed, the <hi>anointing</hi> is ceaſed and departed from them; Your Cauſe is <hi>riſen,</hi> I <hi>feel</hi> it is riſen, The Witneſſes thereof begin to ſtand upon their feet.</p>
            <p>The Intereſt of this ſhort diſcourſe is, Firſt to awaken you, and to point out unto you the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all our <hi>Breakings,</hi> ſince that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Witneſs given from Heaven to our Cauſe. There was much <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> wrath, fooliſhneſs, ſelfiſhneſs, mingled with our <hi>zeal,</hi> Love, Righteouſneſs, in the managing of the Cauſe, which was to be pared and pruned off, <hi>burnt up,</hi> and ſeparated from us, and the fire hath ſeized upon it. There was alſo a <hi>mixt multitude</hi> with us (as there was with <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they came up from <hi>Egypt</hi>) who had not a ſtedfaſt Spirit, nor a right aim, <hi>Children in whom was no faith,</hi> which were to be made <hi>manifeſt,</hi> and to be knockt off. Theſe their <hi>buits</hi> have caught them, and they are at their journeys end; they will be left <hi>hehind,</hi> and that is not the <hi>worſt</hi> that awaits them. While yon had to deal with the <hi>open</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared</hi> Enemy, ye were ſtill ſucceſsful againſt them; but theſe <hi>falſe brethren</hi> have betrayed you and your Cauſe. Truſt them no more, nor <hi>that Spirit:</hi> It is your great advantage, that you now know the <hi>depths of Satan,</hi> you have ſeen Satan transforming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of <hi>light,</hi> the Man of ſin working in all <hi>deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> in praying, preaching, weeping, &amp;c. You cannot be couſened any more with theſe. Where the <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> the <hi>Nature</hi> is, it will recover it ſelf, and this Diſcourſe may be ſerviceable to awaken; and call it forth out of that Caprivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherein it lyes; but where is only the Notion, the Form, the Profeſſion, it will wither away more and more. Let all that are the Children of this Cauſe hear this Voice, and obey this <hi>Call</hi> to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and partake no longer in her <hi>ſins,</hi> as they would not partake in her <hi>Plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond aym of this Diſcourſe, is, to <hi>enlarge</hi> our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the juſt <hi>Extent</hi> and <hi>Dimenſions</hi> of our Cauſe, which is not to be reſtrained or limited by the <hi>ſcant</hi> Models of any private thoughts, but is to be learned and received from the heavenly <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne</hi> as God is pleas'd to let it down and ſhew it unto us. Hence
<pb facs="tcp:119024:4"/>all thoſe Deſigns will be found too <hi>ſhort</hi> or <hi>narrow</hi> of thoſe that would reſt in forming theſe Nations meerely into a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> or that bound the Work by <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Spiritual</hi> liberties, as they are commonly apprehended. The Cauſe of God in its la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and <hi>adaequate</hi> extent, is, the bringing of all things in <hi>Earth</hi> to anſwer the minde of God, as is done in Heaven. A thing not done at <hi>once</hi> nor <hi>preſently,</hi> but by <hi>degrees,</hi> nor to be perfected but by the <hi>appearance</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, as he lets down the ſpiritual knowledge and revelation of himſelf unto us, in the opening of the Scriptures. We are to be <hi>preparing</hi> and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupying our <hi>Meaſures</hi> and Talents, till he come and put the fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing hand to <hi>Crown</hi> his own work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To direct us in the <hi>Way</hi> of ſerving this Cauſe, That we go not forth <hi>headily</hi> and <hi>raſhly,</hi> preſumptuouſly and <hi>ſelf-confidently</hi> in our own <hi>wit, will, wiſdom,</hi> or <hi>rage,</hi> (there hath been too much of this) but humbly waiting upon God, watching and looking up to him, what <hi>door</hi> he opens, what <hi>way</hi> he leads, what <hi>means</hi> he puts into our hands; and not to be troubled if we cannot ſee to the <hi>end</hi> of our way diſtinctly, but from <hi>ſtep</hi> to <hi>ſtep.</hi> If we be brought to an obedient following of him, our way ſhall be as the <hi>encreaſing</hi> light growing to <hi>perfect</hi> day. This was the way God perſwaded the <hi>Parliament</hi> unto at firſt, we had never elſe taken down Biſhops, not being provided of a <hi>Diſcipline</hi> in their room; but God carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us over this Objection then. And ſo this was the way the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> profeſſed themſelves to be lead in, and they proſpered won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully. Thoſe were the days of <hi>innocency</hi> and <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> (though much weakneſs and <hi>childiſhneſs</hi>); and God may upbraid us with that time as once he did <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 2. <hi>I remember thee, the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy youth in the day of thy eſpouſals, when thou followedſt me in a Land that was not ſowed,</hi> (When thou kneweſt not how thou ſhouldſt live, but hadſt every meal from Heaven) <hi>Iſrael was holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. And this is a great thing we have Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and engaged to the Lord. It is no new thing ye are exhorted to, but the <hi>Vowes</hi> of God are upon us. The Lord hath had <hi>livery</hi> and <hi>ſeizin</hi> of us, we have lived upon him, and he hath found us in a <hi>Deſert</hi> Land, and hath borne us upon Eagles wings, and why ſhould it not be ſo again?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:4"/>
            <p>To conclude, let us conſider what a <hi>Name</hi> and a <hi>Praiſe</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be made in the Earth; What people were like <hi>England,</hi> a People ſaved by the Lord! <hi>Shall we begin in the Spirit and ſeek to be made perfect in the fleſh?</hi> Shall we that have been aſſiſted and carryed forth, to aſſert the Cauſe of God againſt the corrupt uſurpations of the World, when they had ſo long <hi>preſcription,</hi> a King of ancient <hi>Deſcent,</hi> that had ſuch a fouundation of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> the <hi>Laws,</hi> an <hi>Army</hi> to ſtand upon, the Spirit of the world in its <hi>vigour</hi> to maintain and uphold them? Shall we that did not then ſhrink, but wrought our Cauſe through the <hi>fire,</hi> and through Seas of <hi>blood;</hi> ſhall we now after we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered all theſe <hi>real</hi> difficulties, be afraid of a thing of <hi>nought,</hi> of the ſhaddows of our own <hi>unbelieving fears,</hi> that have no founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or bottome of <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> or <hi>conſent,</hi> or <hi>conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to urge themſelves upon us? Where is the <hi>King</hi> of whoſe <hi>frown</hi> ye ſhould be afraid? Where's his <hi>Power?</hi> Where's his <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my?</hi> What is become of the <hi>Great</hi> men and <hi>Mighty</hi> men? <hi>Who ſhall hurt you, if ye be followers of that that is good?</hi> If any be ſtept up into their places, and ſhall offer to oppoſe the Canſe of God, ye need not wiſh for <hi>weaker</hi> Adverſaries, for they will be <hi>ſelf-condemned,</hi> They ſtand upon a <hi>Bogg</hi> which will ſwallow them up having no righteous <hi>foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for your Comfort, let me add this one Word; The World ye are to grapple with, hath loſt a great ſtrength of late; Its very Heart-ſtrings are broke. This I muſt ſay for <hi>Him</hi> that is gone, It was <hi>He</hi> that <hi>bare up</hi> this old ruinous Frame, which in likelihood had fallen before this, if His <hi>Parts,</hi> His <hi>Courage,</hi> His <hi>Religion,</hi> had not ſupported it: Whether He did <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill</hi> in it judge ye. Indeed it broke him at length, and he fainted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the weight of it; but He was a ſtrong <hi>Buttreſſe</hi> to it, when it was ſinking in the time of the little <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> had then crackt, if he had not put thereto his ſhoulder. I am not againſt the <hi>Honeſt</hi> Intereſt of the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> or <hi>Law,</hi> if that Intereſt be <hi>publique,</hi> if it be the Intereſt of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> I call them old and rotten in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt State of them wherein at preſent they ſtand; But (I ſay)
<pb facs="tcp:119024:5"/>while that <hi>Prop</hi> of them laſted, there was no attempting againſt them; for God had given him to be a <hi>prolonging</hi> of <hi>days</hi> unto them: And as he that ſtood in the way: did <hi>lett the</hi> revealing of the <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> till he was taken out of the way: ſo the Spirit of God in his poor <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> had not full play againſt this old and corrupt State of things, while that <hi>Great Spirit</hi> acted the <hi>Defence</hi> of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:5"/>
            <head>A Word to the <hi>Reader,</hi> to remove Prejudice.</head>
            <p>MY ayme is to give my <hi>witneſſe</hi> againſt the Preſent <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> whether this Generation will <hi>hear,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will <hi>forbear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have believed, therefore have I ſpoken:</hi> Theſe things are not miniſtred but with ſome <hi>Faith,</hi> that God will appear and <hi>revive</hi> this Cauſe and his poor people: and as I know not which <hi>way,</hi> ſo I am not Solicitous. I would be loath to blow the <hi>Coals</hi> of another Inteſtine <hi>War.</hi> But better our <hi>Peace</hi> be interrupted, then <hi>Truth</hi> periſh; which is more our <hi>Life,</hi> than the <hi>blood</hi> that runs in our Veynes. I know it must be, not by <hi>Might</hi> nor Power, but by the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> that our deliverance is wrought, whether in War or Peace: I ſhould hope, the preſent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations ſhould be too much <hi>ſelf-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> in the Practiſers of them, to bear a <hi>quarrel;</hi> and that if we knew once but how to <hi>Value</hi> our Cauſe and the ground we are upon, our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites would quickly <hi>rebate</hi> their Courage, ſeeing the day is ſo farre riſen.</p>
            <p>I am not againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> as an <hi>unlawful</hi> Government, we find it <hi>owned</hi> of God, and honoured to be a <hi>Type</hi> of the Reign of Chriſt; but I am upon this <hi>Dilemma</hi> withall the Promoters of it here: Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we did <hi>well,</hi> and were guided by a <hi>divine</hi> hand in taking it down, or <hi>not:</hi> If not, why do we not ask the World <hi>mercy,</hi> and reſtore the <hi>old</hi> Family again: If we were directed by God to remove it, let us ſee the ſame divine hand leading to the <hi>reſtoring</hi> it; elſe, What <hi>a ſcandal</hi> is it to our Cauſe, to <hi>build</hi> again the things we <hi>deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God leads us not to it, appears; <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe <hi>his</hi> people <hi>conſent</hi> not in it; and Governments for the <hi>forme</hi> of them are to be <hi>founded</hi> upon <hi>Conſent;</hi> The people that <hi>adhered</hi> and are <hi>yet faithful</hi> to this
<pb facs="tcp:119024:6"/>Cauſe, have not onely their <hi>Intereſt among</hi> others, but <hi>Paramount</hi> to the reſt of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Our Condition <hi>calls</hi> not for <hi>unneceſſary</hi> charge; Taxes lye heavy on the <hi>Commoners;</hi> The <hi>poor</hi> of the Land that want bread, are <hi>numerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Kingly Government is a kind of <hi>Scourge;</hi> and, at beſt, an allay of the <hi>freedome</hi> of a people; a <hi>ſacred</hi> thing eſteem'd, of difficult <hi>acceſſe,</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrouſly <hi>adored,</hi> an occaſion of great <hi>ſuperfluity</hi> exceſſe and vanity, unſuitable to this day that is upon us; and laſtly, makes the Perſon too ſtour and haughty to fall under the reproofs of the poor mean ſervants of Chriſt, that come to them onely in the name of the Lord; and ſo exalts their hearts to their own destruction in the end, and the people's ſmart in the mean time.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> were Types, but Types are <hi>Ceaſed. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is now to be preſerved in the Perſon of Christ, He will adminiſter it in <hi>Truth,</hi> in the truth of his own righteous and royal ſpirit, not in <hi>figure</hi> and ſhadow, through pitiful poor baſe men, ſervants of lusts. The pooreſt Saint that <hi>Cobbles</hi> under a Stall hath more of <hi>true</hi> Majeſty, and is more a King then the greateſt Prince among them, that is under the power of <hi>luſt</hi> in his <hi>own</hi> ſoul.</p>
            <p>I might give many other Reaſons, as the <hi>Impolitiqueneſſe</hi> of it to make <hi>a Family-quarrel;</hi> the <hi>unſafeneſs</hi> of it, for the perſon or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily we ſhould ſo ſet up. But I leave politiques to <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> I am chiefly exerciſed in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the thing.</p>
            <p>The like I ſay for <hi>Lords,</hi> I am not againſt Lords <hi>ſimply.</hi> But they are thrown out; It concerns us to conſider by what hand, and on what <hi>grounds,</hi> before we admit them again. If they were <hi>unneceſſary</hi> and <hi>hinderful</hi> of our Cauſe and proceedings, either we have <hi>altered</hi> our Cauſe, or they are ſo ſtill. It was not the <hi>Perſons</hi> we animadverted against but the <hi>Power:</hi> How unrighteous is it, if our Judgments be altered of the Power, to place it in <hi>New</hi> Perſons, when many of the <hi>Ancient</hi> Peers are yet living, as deſerving as the New. Is not this the way to breed a quarrel between <hi>Peers</hi> and Peers, as between <hi>King</hi> and King.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Walk not in the way of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> The <hi>Judgment</hi> of God made Kings; <hi>Kings,</hi> made <hi>Lords;</hi> They were onely to <hi>help</hi> the King to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave</hi> the people. What people that had their <hi>choice</hi> would ſet up <hi>either? Lords</hi> without <hi>Lands,</hi> can do no more ſervice for God nor their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then <hi>other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:6"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I am not againſt a <hi>Diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Ranks</hi> of men. <hi>Variety</hi> is the <hi>beauty</hi> of the univerſe, and an exerciſe of <hi>Vertue.</hi> Where would <hi>bounty</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> be, if there were not <hi>Rich?</hi> And where were <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>contentation</hi> of mind, if there were not <hi>mean</hi> men? I would have every one have their <hi>Rights,</hi> no induſtrious men <hi>want,</hi> all honest men <hi>free.</hi> I would not <hi>affectedly</hi> ſet up <hi>mean</hi> men againſt the wealthy, nor would <hi>Itye</hi> wiſdome and <hi>underſtanding</hi> to men of <hi>Eſtate.</hi> Liberal, and <hi>generous</hi> Education, is a good quality; but let it not go <hi>alone</hi> in the choice of men to rule: but look for the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> It is far from me to <hi>Monopolize</hi> or ingroſſe (in my judgment) the <hi>priviledges</hi> and advantages of that Righteous Kingdome which God is ſetting up over the Earth, to Saints onely; which ſhall be ſhared among all that ſubmit to it, and oppoſe it not ſo far as they are <hi>Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> much leſſe do I reckon of <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> by any <hi>form</hi> of words that men expreſſe themſelves in. And though I dare not <hi>abett</hi> all that are zealous for this Cauſe for Saints, yet I muſt profeſſe my faith <hi>is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> concerning thoſe that deſert it; and it is an argument of ſome more <hi>Noble,</hi> if not <hi>divine</hi> thing in men, through all <hi>Shocks</hi> of temptations on the one hand, and the other, to preſerve their Integrity. And this I am perſwaded; As, many have bin already ſhaken off, (as untimely figgs); ſo few or none will hold out with this good Cauſe to the <hi>end, but,</hi> thoſe that are of an <hi>Incorruptible</hi> ſeed: whom therefore I ſhall deſire to know by their <hi>fruits,</hi> and judge of them according to their <hi>works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> And, as I am not able to ſay but a ſpirit of righteous Government as to things between <hi>man</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> may be found in ſome who are not Saints upon the <hi>Stricteſt</hi> account of <hi>regeneration,</hi> (who may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for ought I know, have the exerciſe of their talent <hi>allowed</hi> them even in the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſubjecting that Rule of theirs in due ſubſerviency to the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> &amp; <hi>Spiritual</hi> affaires): ſo can I not on the other hand admitt that to be the <hi>proper</hi> Rule and Government of Christ, be it exerciſed by whomſoever (though the <hi>Higheſt</hi> Profeſſors in Religion, and on never ſo high an account) that is contrary to the light of <hi>Scripture</hi> rightly underſtood, or the light of <hi>incorrupt Reaſon</hi> in any ſort of men. The <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and the righteouſneſs of that Kingdome juſtifying its ſelf undeniably to the conſcience of the <hi>natural</hi> man, in things that are under his Judgment, as well as
<pb facs="tcp:119024:7"/>to the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Chriſtian in things which are proper to his diſcerning: So as there is no <hi>Arbitrarineſs</hi> here in this Kingdome, but all by <hi>Rule,</hi> and that Rule is ſo <hi>clear</hi> and undenyable, as nothing can riſe up against it in any mans conſcience.</p>
            <p>Lastly, I deſire I may be believed, that I have not bin led by any <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt his preſent Highneſſe in this Teſtimony which I bear, who as He hath not by any <hi>Publique</hi> Act of his Government diſobliged any (that I know of), ſo by his affability and Courteſie wins upon all (if any <hi>private</hi> paſſages have not bin ſo to the <hi>Rule,</hi> I would not <hi>mention</hi> them becauſe I would not <hi>multiply</hi> them.) As the Place he is in, ſought him, not he it; ſo I deſire, He may lay it and himſelf at the feet of Chriſt, to diſpoſe of him and his Intereſt, as may be moſt for his glory. So is he ſure not to be layd-by <hi>diſhonourably,</hi> if any could have a heart or ſtomach ſo to do. <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> muſt give up the Kingdome to <hi>God,</hi> and ſo must all <hi>Rulers</hi> and Potentates unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> elſe Wo be to them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119024:7"/>
            <head>THE Cauſe of God, AND Of theſe Nations.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the deplorable Estate of the Nation at this day, after ſo fair advantages as were put into our hands.</head>
               <p>IT is a certain truth, No man is made <hi>unhappy</hi> but by his own <hi>choice;</hi> God hath not bin wanting to let us find, that all the <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of our enemies either at home or abroad could not deſtroy us, while we had <hi>hearts,</hi> and were <hi>watchfull,</hi> to uſe the <hi>means</hi> to preſerve our ſeivs: confidence in men and diſtruſt in God, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go together, and are much of like dangerous Iſſue and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. We have loſt more in this ſeven years <hi>Peace,</hi> by truſting too much to a friend, then we did in all our twelve years war, while we conflicted with hoaſts of enemies; inaſmuch as we have been ſtill loſing our liberty by little and little, which all the time of the wars we went on gaining more and more: and if we get no more by loſing him, but reſolution to take up our truſt, we ſhall be confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gainers. I am (I confeſſe) ſo much a <hi>Leveller,</hi> that in this corrupt ſtate of mens principles and minds, (corruptible at the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119024:8"/>beſt), it is ſafer for <hi>Laws</hi> to govern than <hi>Men.</hi> Not but that, that bleſſed day of the Lord's own righteous Reign, may be neerer the dawning upon us, than perhaps the preſent dark and cloudy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of our thoughts and affairs would ſeem to hold forth: Therefore I would not have the door of a lively expectation ſhut againſt our Lord's appearing as I would not that, in the mean time, (though we knew, He were to come to morrow) we ſhould throw away our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and put out our Lights (as <hi>men</hi>), and deſpiſe thoſe liberties he hath given us as advantages for our ſerving of him.</p>
               <p>The late violent turns and changes that have befallen this poor Commonwealth, ſince our Arms reſted from the common enemy, have (to my apprehenſion) lookt more like the <hi>Trumpets</hi> in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> that, with gallantry and ſtate, brought in <hi>Corruption,</hi> than the <hi>Vials</hi> that work <hi>it</hi> out. Theſe pour not forth themſelves at <hi>once</hi> with <hi>obſervation,</hi> but <hi>leiſurely</hi> and ſecretly waſt and conſume <hi>long-rooted</hi> Uſurpations. And all that either the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Military</hi> power hath to do, is but to maintain us in peace and <hi>freedom,</hi> that ſo we may attend unto that <hi>Light</hi> of God (which, according to the prophecies of Scripture, is breaking forth) which will certainly <hi>undermine</hi> and deſtroy the State <hi>Anti-chriſtian,</hi> as well as the Church Anti chriſtian: for there is both, and both ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt's mouth and the <hi>brightneſſe</hi> of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: And without his appointment, it will never be done by <hi>ſecular</hi> Sword or Arm.</p>
               <p>When I ſay The Powers are to <hi>maintain</hi> our peace and freedom, I am aware what I ſay, and that it implyes, We were in the <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of them; and indeed ſo we were, and they were given us of <hi>God:</hi> If it be demanded, <hi>when</hi> we were ſo, and wherein it appeared? I anſwer, When our Arms were <hi>victorious</hi> over all our enemies in the field, which was not till after <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight: Then was there nothing in our way <hi>viſibly,</hi> but Mercy and Truth, Righteouſneſſe and Peace might have embraced each other.</p>
               <p>The Enemy was ſubdued in <hi>England</hi> before that, but there was a remnant of him in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> And then the <hi>Rent</hi> that was made among us by the taking off the King, <hi>weakned</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Intereſt much, as the Action it ſelf gave opportunity to the <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious</hi> aſpirings and deſigns of ſome, (when that place was empty) to get into it, (at leaſt wiſe ſuch <hi>jealouſies</hi> there were). Perhaps, when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119024:8"/>that action ſhall be reveiw'd by us in <hi>Cooler</hi> Spirits, we may ſee Cauſe to acknowledge that the King was not ſo ripe for the Capital Juſtice of man in thoſe <hi>paſſive</hi> Circumſtances, wherein he then ſtood as a <hi>Priſoner</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> till he had forfeited the <hi>ſecurity</hi> we might have laid upon him; I am ſure our <hi>Eager</hi> policy in that Action for <hi>ſelf-preſervation</hi> hath little ſucceded or anſwered our deſires. However the ſickle of <hi>Divine</hi> Juſtice cutting him down, it was not <hi>adviſeable</hi> for honeſt men (when they had <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged</hi> their judgments and conſciences in a ſaithful teſtimony) to <hi>divide</hi> thereupon; But notwithſtanding this <hi>breach,</hi> we were again, as I ſaid, upon <hi>fair</hi> advantages after the Battle at <hi>Worcester,</hi> when nothing was wanting but a <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi> to manage ſo great an <hi>opportunity.</hi> A time like that of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> When our Saviour was born all the <hi>World</hi> was <hi>quiet;</hi> So was all our <hi>little</hi> world, for the Saviour to be born into it the 2d time. Tyrants both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> expel'd, their <hi>Armyes</hi> vanquiſht: The Nations like <hi>wax</hi> ready to receive any good and righteous <hi>impreſſion:</hi> yea, the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf expecting what good thing would be <hi>required</hi> of them to do; having power to <hi>refuſe,</hi> nothing ſhould have bin <hi>demanded.</hi> The <hi>Lawyers</hi> quaked, the <hi>formal</hi> Clergy were down in the Mouth, the <hi>Malignant</hi> trembled, the <hi>looſe</hi> Nobility and Gentry lookt <hi>pale;</hi> All men were frighted into a fear and awe of <hi>God,</hi> and the hearts and expectations of all <hi>good</hi> men were up ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. But wherefore is a <hi>price</hi> put into the hand of a <hi>fool,</hi> when there is no <hi>heart?</hi> Now was the time that God ſaid unto us, as once unto <hi>Iſrael, Go up and poſſeſſe the Land</hi> which I have ſworn that I would give you, Go fill the Land with <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> plant my <hi>Name</hi> and my <hi>Truth</hi> there; Drive out all <hi>profanneſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſſe, injuſtice, oppreſſion;</hi> eaſe the <hi>burdens,</hi> break the <hi>yokes, relieve</hi> the <hi>neceſſities</hi> of my people, ſtamp my <hi>Image</hi> upon the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; conſecrate it to me; whatever thing in your minds that is <hi>honeſt,</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>merciful,</hi> bring it forth and fear not, <hi>for the Lord your God which goeth before you, He ſhall fight for you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all that He did for you in</hi> Egypt. He that brought you up from under <hi>Regal</hi> Tyranny, and <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> domination, that hath vanquiſhed the Enemy in the three Nations before you, and all their formidable hoſts, He is with you. (4.) <hi>This</hi> was the <hi>poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of the Land which the Lord called his people then unto; Even
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119024:9"/>to fill the ſeats of <hi>Judicature,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> places and <hi>things</hi> with the <hi>preſence</hi> of God; not to ſatisfie our ſelves, to poſſeſſe the <hi>King's</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> Lands, and <hi>Deane</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> Lands, or rather to be <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> by them.</p>
               <p>All men muſt here needs underſtand that I charge the <hi>Army.</hi> And indeed I do ſo, though not them alone, but many of the then <hi>Parliament,</hi> who took a <hi>new ſcent,</hi> of the <hi>Honors promotions</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> of thoſe whom God had caſt out before them, and loſt the ſcent of the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> yea, and many of the <hi>zealous</hi> people of the Nation too were taken off by theſe things. Theſe were the <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> ſnares that inveigled the <hi>Princes.</hi> And what hath fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereupon is ſad to behold at this day. We having loſt in a manner all that we had got, and being relapſt deeper into bondage then heretofore in the <hi>Kings</hi> time; He is not an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> that doth not bleed to ſee how ſince that Liberty is <hi>loſt,</hi> Property <hi>expos'd</hi> to Arbitrary Luſt and <hi>Will,</hi> The <hi>Publique</hi> Cauſe and Intereſt laid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, A <hi>Private</hi> Cauſe and Intereſt ſet up, Men <hi>ſworn</hi> to it, <hi>Judged</hi> by it, not only as to <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>livelyhood,</hi> (Officers being Caſher'd the Army, and others put out of Places of Truſt) but ſome put to <hi>death</hi> for not preferring it before the publique; <hi>Malignants</hi> countenanced and taken into favour, occaſion given to the <hi>formal,</hi> yea, the <hi>profane</hi> ſpirit, to lift up its head, while <hi>publique</hi> ſpirits and the <hi>precious</hi> of the Land were diſcouraged; yea, that <hi>very</hi> ſpirit whereby our Cauſe <hi>roſe</hi> and obtain'd ſo far, lookt upon as an <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and watcht over with a <hi>jealous</hi> eye. <hi>Tryers</hi> ſet up to keep it out of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> good <hi>Juſtices</hi> removed, and the <hi>old</hi> ſpirit of the <hi>Gentry</hi> brought in play again, worldly <hi>greatneſſe</hi> again affected by thoſe that ſometime ſeemed <hi>to</hi> ſet their face <hi>another</hi> way. The <hi>burdenſome</hi> pompe and vanity of a <hi>Court</hi> again revived, and <hi>idle</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons therein entertained, and maintained upon the charge of the poor exhauſted <hi>Commoners;</hi> juſtice as much <hi>delayed,</hi> as before; the Lawyers, as <hi>Corrupt</hi> and <hi>Exorbitant:</hi> Thoſe <hi>Bawbles</hi> (as once they were deem'd and ſtyled) and ridiculous <hi>formalities</hi> of <hi>State</hi> again introduced, as vain and exceſſive <hi>Feastings;</hi> and as ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous <hi>Funerals,</hi> as in the darkeſt times; in all theſe things, as if we ſhould profeſſe to glory in our ſhame. The election of Members to ſit in Parliament, as <hi>Corruptly</hi> negotiated and <hi>ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> as in the Kings time, Armies modelled and imployed not for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119024:9"/>maintaining of the Cauſe of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Nations,</hi> (ſave onely in name and <hi>title</hi>) but indeed and in <hi>truth</hi> to maintain <hi>thoſe</hi> that have Uſurpt the <hi>Diſpoſe</hi> of us, and it, and all our Liberties. A Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil receiving <hi>paye,</hi> for work the Nation never ſet them upon: When others would ſerve <hi>gratis.</hi> Nehemiah <hi>did not ſo,</hi> nor the former Council of State, though they had their faults. In a word, all things running again in the <hi>old</hi> Channel, and not onely King, Lords, and Biſhops ſet up again under <hi>new appellations;</hi> but even the <hi>old</hi> Names and Powers claym'd and contended for, as to the two firſt; The <hi>Negative</hi> Voyce, and the <hi>Militia</hi> it ſelf not excepted, (two main branches of the late Quarrel): and if theſe ſucceed to the deſire of ſome (as, if we look to <hi>humane</hi> probabilities, there may be too much Cauſe of fear, when we conſider what attempts were made, and what means were uſed the <hi>laſt</hi> Parliament to have made a <hi>King</hi>) we muſt have <hi>Biſhops</hi> too, if the old <hi>Proverb</hi> (which was no doubt the reſult of a deliberate conſideration and inſpection in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Nature</hi> of the two Intereſts, <hi>No Biſhop no King</hi>) do hold good.</p>
               <p>While theſe things have bin doing, the hand of God hath bin upon our <hi>Bodies,</hi> our <hi>Cattel,</hi> our <hi>Trading.</hi> What ſtrange and <hi>New</hi> diſeaſes have ſwept away whole Families and <hi>Townes,</hi> almoſt of late years; So, as we could not avoid taking notice of an intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divine <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> therein: Unnatural and <hi>intemperate</hi> ſeaſons, a plague among our <hi>Horſes,</hi> wherein, perhaps we have too much confided, Our <hi>Merchants</hi> break and run away daily, Our <hi>Ships</hi> loſt and taken to incredible numbers; Our <hi>Men</hi> (the ſtrength of our Nation) ſent to digg their <hi>graves</hi> with their ſwords in <hi>forreign</hi> Countries and diſagreeing <hi>Climats,</hi> whither they are <hi>preſt</hi> forth againſt their <hi>Conſent</hi> (a thing that would not have bin put up for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) and the <hi>Poor</hi> of the Land <hi>increaſing</hi> wonderfully upon us, whole <hi>Families</hi> ready to ſtarve for want of <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Imployment,</hi> whilſt that which would maintain many Thouſands is laviſht (I may ſay imbezeld) to keep up the <hi>Port</hi> of a few <hi>new rais'd</hi> great Ones, at an <hi>unneceſſary</hi> height.</p>
               <p>Where theſe things may <hi>End,</hi> or whereto they are <hi>directed</hi> in the Intentions of <hi>many,</hi> that drive them on, the Lord alone knows: but it is much, and with too much ground (or appearance of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood) ſuſpected, to be with an eye to bring-in the <hi>old Family</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119024:10"/>aſſoon as they have made all things ready; which by that time all is ſaid that theſe <hi>Deſigners</hi> are able to alleadge of the <hi>Commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> thereof, to put us out of fear of any more <hi>Warrs</hi> and Changes, and to ſave the <hi>Charge</hi> of maintaining Armies, to keep out that <hi>Title;</hi> I fear the Nation may have too ſtrong a <hi>Temptation</hi> unto: And then what will become (I ſay not) of King's and Biſhops <hi>Lands,</hi> which many of the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Sould'ers</hi> have ſwallowed down, (it were the leſſe matter if the <hi>diſgorging</hi> of them were the worſt conſequence); but what would become of the <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Libert'es,</hi> not to ſay the <hi>Lives,</hi> of all <hi>honeſt</hi> men that have <hi>adhered</hi> to this Cauſe? Nay, what would become of the <hi>Cauſe of God</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which we have bin contending for againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe;</hi> let every indifferent perſon Judge. Though the truth is, ſetting theſe conſequences aſide, if there were a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of a King again, I muſt profeſſe I ſhould think it more <hi>righteous,</hi> yea, more <hi>honourable</hi> for our <hi>principles</hi> and our Cauſe, to take a branch of the old Family that hath not <hi>forfeited</hi> his Right by actual <hi>hosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> againſt us, than to ſet up any <hi>other</hi> Family in that place, ſo little grudge have I againſt that <hi>expulſed</hi> Family: though I think whoſoever pretends to be their <hi>Friend,</hi> and ſhould wiſh them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to that <hi>Office</hi> and Dignity in <hi>this Day,</hi> wherein God ſeems to be overthrowing <hi>(deſignedly)</hi> the <hi>throne</hi> of kingdoms, conſults nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>theirs</hi> nor the <hi>Nations</hi> peace.</p>
               <p>But, which is the Miſery of all the reſt, There are not wanting that endeavour to perſwade us, that though theſe ſymptomes of <hi>death</hi> are upon us, yet we are <hi>well</hi> and upon an excellent <hi>constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> (What would ye have? May ye not be as good as ye will, ſay they?) and that <hi>this</hi> is our Cauſe we fought for. Which is ſo true, as that the <hi>Calves</hi> were <hi>Iſrael's Gods,</hi> that brought them up out of the land of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> As if the ſetting up a <hi>few</hi> men, that <hi>ſeemed</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>zealous</hi> for the Cauſe, were the triumphing of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> when the <hi>body</hi> of the Adherents <hi>languiſh.</hi> God knowes whether in this I do enviouſly detract from the <hi>Merits</hi> of any (His late <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> or others, that roſe with him) who deſerved <hi>eminently</hi> in their day; And None, was more joy'd to ſee the <hi>power</hi> come into <hi>His</hi> hands then thoſe that have ſince had ſo much cauſe to bewail the <hi>ill uſe</hi> of it. But, to take it ill of us, that we cannot <hi>dance</hi> and <hi>ſing</hi> in theſe circumſtances, is ſuch an <hi>unreaſonableneſſe</hi> as is amazing. Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119024:10"/>not that men that have been <hi>free,</hi> ſhould think it irkſom to be in <hi>bondage;</hi> That thoſe that have purchaſed their liberty at ſuch a <hi>Rate,</hi> ſhould be willing to enjoy it; That thoſe Court <hi>Trinkets</hi> and <hi>Foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> thoſe chargeable <hi>Bawbles</hi> and Vanities being once caſt out, are not without <hi>regret</hi> and anguiſh received and taken in again, No, No: we cannot ſo eaſily take upon us all the <hi>Blood</hi> that hath been ſhed in this Quarrell; we cannot ſtate the cauſe upon a <hi>Perſon</hi> or a <hi>Family,</hi> or the <hi>individuall</hi> circumſtances of <hi>Hic &amp; Nunc:</hi> Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is Tyranny, and Oppreſſion is Oppreſſion, be it excerciſed by <hi>whomſoever;</hi> and ſuperfluity and luxury are worſe in this <hi>Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> than in the former daies.</p>
               <p>A liberty there is (I grant) to ſay what you will againſt the <hi>old Court,</hi> the <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> the waies of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and former Tyrants and perſecutors, and to profeſſe and practiſe any thing that touches not <hi>preſent</hi> Corruptions: but ſhall we have liberty to witneſſe againſt the ſame <hi>Evills</hi> in new <hi>dreſſes?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">May Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a Healing Q.? <hi>A.</hi> No: If he do, he muſt, for an anſwer, be ſent to <hi>Cariſbrook</hi> Caſtle. May Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> Lt. Gen. <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and other faithful Officers in the Army freely remonſtrate againſt incroaching Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny? No: they muſt then be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhier'd and ſent to the Tower. May <hi>Mr. Cardel</hi> freely preach againſt a formal Miniſtry and Worſhip? No: He muſt then leave his Benefice in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet.</hi> May Mr. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> try the Tryers? No: He muſt then be ſchool'd for his pains, and know that He that ſet them up will maintain them. May Major Gen. <hi>Overton</hi> exerciſe his command freely without ſerving the luſts of great ones? No: He muſt then be baniſhed to the Iſle of <hi>Garnſey.</hi>
                  </note> If not, what liberty have we? or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what liberty can be <hi>expected?</hi> when thoſe that take upon them to <hi>meaſure</hi> it out to us, are themſelves the great Object of <hi>Offence,</hi> and have made themſelves deſervedly the very <hi>Butt</hi> againſt which all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>witneſſing</hi> muſt be directed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will put out our eyes, the light of our <hi>Reaſon</hi> and our <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> and call Evil <hi>Good,</hi> and Good <hi>Evill,</hi> as too many have been corrupted or deceived to do, in theſe daies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119024:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Enquires the Remedy in this caſe, where the forwardneſs of the natural Man is rejected, and it is ſhewed, That by the firſt Covenant there is no recovery for us, if God ſhew us not a better Covenant, and bring not down our Spirits to the tearms thereof.</head>
               <p>THe Caſe ſtanding thus with us, the Queſtion will be, What way of <hi>recovery</hi> is there for us? The <hi>fleſh</hi> and the naturall Man is <hi>forward</hi> and bold, and would be <hi>undertaking</hi> preſently, like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old; who, when they had offended the Lord, with refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to <hi>go up</hi> at his command, thought to mend all again preſently with changing their <hi>reſolution;</hi> But the Lord tells them, It would not be <hi>accepted</hi> then: Becauſe they would not go up in <hi>his Time,</hi> they ſhould not go up in <hi>their own;</hi> If they did, they ſhould <hi>fall</hi> before the <hi>Canaanites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and an opportunity, which if it be let ſlip, is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> to be recovered again, as it was with <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> O that thou hadſt known, at leaſt in <hi>this thy day,</hi> the things that belong to thy peace; but <hi>now</hi> they are hid from thine <hi>eys.</hi> Ye ſhall <hi>deſire</hi> to ſee <hi>one</hi> of the daies of the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> and ſhall not <hi>not</hi> ſee it. The night cometh wherein <hi>no man can work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There is a day of <hi>grace,</hi> wherein God makes <hi>offers</hi> and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his preſence and aſſiſtance, which is meant by <hi>the daies of the Son of Man;</hi> wherein the patience of God waits upon the world, <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> not leaving himſelf without <hi>Witneſſe</hi> that he is ready to do all on his part, towards the ſaving and redeeming of them. Thus the <hi>old World</hi> had their day, during the preaching of <hi>Noah:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had theirs, during the preaching of <hi>Chriſt, All men</hi> have their day wherein God ſhews himſelf, not willing of their death. And thus <hi>England</hi> hath had its day, as hath been ſhewed. But if this be overſlipped then follows,</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place, the day of <hi>Judgment, Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27. <hi>If we ſin wilfully after we have received the knowledg of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſin, but a certain fearful looking
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119024:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>for of judgment and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries;</hi> That which <hi>grace</hi> will not do, <hi>judgment</hi> ſhall. There is an <hi>Order</hi> for the iſſuing out of all Gods Attributes: though he have magnified his <hi>Word</hi> above all his Name, and given it the firſt place; yet he hath not ceaſed to be <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> he muſt make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ſtoop to him, elſe he had as good give up his Kingdom. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>When the Maſter of the houſe is riſen up, and hath ſhut to the door, and ye ſhall begin to ſtand without and knock, &amp;c.</hi> then, though <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> ſtood before me, my heart could not be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this people. In that age when the <hi>Jews</hi> were rejected, they had many friends that were powerful with God, the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and others; yet they could not prevail to bring back the heart of God to that people; though <hi>Paul</hi> bids high and would have given his ſalvation for it: No the <hi>fire</hi> muſt now work upon them; Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt have its courſe, the <hi>Decree</hi> is gone forth, there is no <hi>arreſting</hi> of it. And though God will take up again and be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled <hi>at laſt,</hi> yea and with more abundant kindneſs gather his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple again; yet it muſt be through a <hi>long tract</hi> of ſuffering, a 1600 years rejection, and no hopes given them till Jeſus Chriſt be ſent the ſecond time, in the glory of the Father to reſtore them.</p>
               <p>Let this be conſidered: for if this be our caſe, that the door be ſhut, and that we begin to ſtand without and knock (as me-thinks it looks too like ſuch a thing, we have not that ſucceſs and <hi>admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within</hi> that formerly we had) we ſhall receive but cold anſwers <hi>without doors;</hi> then deliverance muſt be wrought through the <hi>fire:</hi> we muſt <hi>bear our iniquity,</hi> before God be pacified towards us.</p>
               <p>But we have been ſo <hi>dandled</hi> and playd with, that, like wanton children not uſed to be laſht, we know not how to underſtand cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; but are ready to think God is playing with us, when he is laying the rod upon us. Thus it was with us all the dayes of the late <hi>Protector,</hi> we put all upon the account of <hi>jeſt</hi> and <hi>tryal;</hi> All our loſſes abroad of ſhips and me (ſplitting our Deſigns) we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them but as tryals, And things running Counter at home to honeſt principles and expectation, we thought they were but <hi>miſts</hi> caſt before our eys; ſure the day would clear up, and things would go well at length. Though ſome felt the rod to ſmart,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119024:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>others call'd it play and ſport: therefore we had need to be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to know where we are, that the rod is upon us, and if we underſtand not <hi>Jezreel, Loruhamah</hi> follows: and if that ſpeak not loud enough, <hi>Loammi</hi> will. You may obſerve in that firſt of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> the Prophet had three children, The firſt he was appointed to call <hi>Jezreel,</hi> that was as the firſt drops of the ſhowr of vengeance; now <hi>Iſrael</hi> look to thy ſelf, and remember the day of <hi>Jezreel,</hi> what <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi> did ſerving <hi>himſelf</hi> when he pretended to ſerve me; I will therefore viſit, ſaith God, the blood of <hi>Jezreel</hi> on the houſe of <hi>Jehu:</hi> There was the <hi>warning piece</hi> ſhot off, which might have its uſefulneſs to ſome tender-hearted <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to drive them into their Chambers till the indignation was over paſt. Thoſe that were not awakened by this, hear next of <hi>Loruhamah,</hi> I will no more have mercy: And if this do not full execution, <hi>Loammi</hi> follows, Ye are not my people. To apply this, Our Mercy runs low already, but when God ſhall declare againſt us, as not his people, we ſhall be ſenſible of his diſpleaſure too late.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A particular enquiry into the immediate Cauſes of this dangerous relapſe of ours.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ENGLAND</hi> hath had many <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> yet have I met with few that have hit upon the <hi>very Cauſe</hi> of this relapſe of ours, or that preſcribe a proper and ſufficient remedy, though many pens are at work, and many brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirits give their Eſſay, (ſay much and very well, as to the reſcuing our too far gone liberty, and more do ſigh and mourn, not able to utter and vent the grief of their hearts <hi>(Curae leves loquuntur, ingentes stupent)</hi> But few go to the <hi>Root</hi> of our diſtemper, we muſt go lower yet;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119024:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sure that which hath blaſted all our hopes, and made us return and ſit down as men aſhamed <hi>re infectâ,</hi> muſt be diſcovered, and this Light I am apt to think muſt come out of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> Thoſe that have travelled through the like paſſages in their own hearts, and have known the <hi>depths of Satan,</hi> the admirable ſhapes he tranſforms himſelf into, and what an abſolute <hi>Newneſs</hi> of life and frame of Spirit, is requiſite for the carrying on the work of the Kingdom of God <hi>ſteadily,</hi> and without ſtarting back, they may tell us ſomething of importance and ſiguificancy in our Caſe.</p>
               <p>In ſearching out the Root of our Diſtemper, we may profitably reflect upon many things which might be <hi>partly</hi> Cauſes of it, and have a hand in bringing us thus low, when we were in ſo <hi>hopeful</hi> a way (as was hinted before.) Such as are, a carnal <hi>Succumbency</hi> of Spirit, lying down in the advantanges attained: and ſo making the Kingdom of God a thing <hi>too outward,</hi> conſiſting in worldly and outward eaſe, honour, and the like, and neglecting it within. 2. Making it too private and narrow, contenting our ſelves with our own, not travelling of others <hi>deliverance,</hi> the poor remaining yet in ſtreights in our own Land, through want of <hi>juſtice</hi> to help them to their own, and want of mercy to extend ſomething of ours to them. 3. <hi>Unwatchfulneſs</hi> of Spirit, through which the enemy got an advantage to work in the night of our ſecurity and ſloth, to undo all again; while we were ſleeping and ſhorting in our private advantages. And many ſuch like Reaſons might be aſſigned, which if we ſhould be exact to muſter up, we might be loſt in them.</p>
               <p>But they being infirmities of <hi>all Times</hi> common to all as Men, they have their <hi>eaſier</hi> and more ordinary cenſure and pardon from the Lord, and cannot be ſuppoſed to be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely animadvered againſt by the hand of his juſtice, as to cauſe him after ſuch <hi>intimacy,</hi> to turn his back upon a people. And therefore we muſt ſearch for ſome other <hi>blacker</hi> and fowler thing to charge this great <hi>Deſertion</hi> and ſorſaking of us upon.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119024:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And as Phyſitians uſe to inquire of their Patients the <hi>time</hi> when their diſeaſes ſeized upon them, and the <hi>Manner</hi> of its on-ſet, <hi>how</hi> and <hi>where</hi> it found them? where they had bin? what they had bin <hi>doing?</hi> what they had <hi>eaten</hi> or <hi>drank</hi> that day? or what <hi>exerciſe</hi> they had bin at? and ſuch like Circumſiances: ſo let us <hi>do.</hi> We may remember, that it was a conſtant obſervation which was again and again inculcated upon us, both by the Lord himſelf, and thoſe that were wiſe <hi>obſervers</hi> of his providences and diſpenſations, that when ever we began to conſult with <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> and to deal <hi>wiſely,</hi> to reſtrain or deal hardly with the <hi>true Iſrael of God;</hi> The Lord did alwayes animadvert againſt us with ſome loſſe, <hi>ill ſucceſſe,</hi> or diſappointment in our publique affaires, which was as that voice unto us, <hi>Touch not mine annointed and do my Prophets no harme.</hi> It is for their ſakes that God doth all, that he rebukes Kings, He gives Nations for them, and therefore not to diſcern this, (the Lords <hi>body,</hi> whoſe good and deliverance is the ſcope and aime of all God's works and diſpenſations), No wonder if it caſt us into a ſick and weak and languiſhing Eſtate: By theſe we <hi>roſe,</hi> with theſe we <hi>thrived.</hi> It may be remembred, Our affaires never ſucceeded, till they came to be managed by <hi>theſe</hi> hands in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and then we had not any conſiderable ſtop or Check that did dwell upon us, till the ſalvation of the three Nations was wrought out and accompliſhed. But when God had Vanquiſhed our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I dowell remember an evil ſpirit grew up againſt the people of God, we grew jealous of them, we were glad to be <hi>Saved</hi> by them, but afraid they ſhould <hi>Rule</hi> over us: And therefore as their <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> unwatchfulneſſe and unheedfulneſſe to this ſpirit gave way, (thoſe that ſhould have prevented and forbid, being otherwiſe <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately</hi> taken up and employed, or wanting ſuch a ſenſe and value of themſelves in the Lord, as <hi>was</hi> requiſite to keep off the World from preſuming and <hi>incroaching</hi> upon them) by little and little they grew from jealouſie to <hi>Emnity,</hi> and to plant their Engines againſt that people and that <hi>ſpirit</hi> that had bin their <hi>Raepart</hi> and defence, in all aſſaults that had bin made againſt their peace and ſafety. Nay, then ſayes <hi>God,</hi> if this be your <hi>Requital</hi> of me, if you that have bin fellow Souldiers in one Cauſe, fellow ſervants in one houſe, know no better how to uſe your peace and liberty, but fall <hi>a beating your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſervants;</hi> I will make one among you, or I will ſend in <hi>One</hi> upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119024:13"/>you, that ſhall <hi>ſeize and ſecure</hi> things you ſo abuſe, not to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red again, till you know how to make a better uſe of them. You love your Liberty, you love your property, you are not for Me, nor will give my Saints their Liberty, and free breathing among you: if ye drive me away from you, if I go up from you, theſe go with me. And as for thoſe you Maligne, I will be <hi>a little Sanctuary</hi> to them.</p>
               <p>And there is this thing farther in it, which is worthy our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, The ſpirit we were ſo jealous of, was that <hi>growing light</hi> in the people of God, which we knew not where it would end, being a free born Creation that had no name nor <hi>form:</hi> for that which was formed, we could admit and grew pretty familiar with, though at firſt we were ſhy of ſome of them, as Independents, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c. But this nameleſſe thing, this <hi>Virgin</hi> that was not eſpouſed nor determined to or by any forme; This ſpirit that owned no Father but God, no Maſter but one, and He in Heaven; that was in a pure abſolute and conſtant dependance on him that profeſſed to <hi>follow the Lamb</hi> whitherſoever he ſhould go, that had reſigned its will, its wiſdome, the <hi>Conduct</hi> of it ſelf wholly to him, This was the Offence: Top and keep down this ſpirit, let not this get the head of us; if it do, we are undone; our Religion, our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistency</hi> is gone, we ſhall be the moſt toſſed wavering uncertain fluid ridiculous people in the World. No Nation will value us, none of the <hi>Poteſtant</hi> Churches will own us. Let not this Man, let not any men in this ſpirit Rule over us, nor be ſuffered among us.</p>
               <p>Now mark what God did, He took one that was in <hi>no form,</hi> neither <hi>Presbyterian, Independent,</hi> nor <hi>Anapatiſt,</hi> and ſets him up in deſpight of all this wit and contrivance to the contrary; And ſo the very thing, that generation ſo ſtudiouſly avoyed, fell unto them. <hi>The thing they feared</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaies) <hi>came unpon them,</hi> and that very life they ſought to ſave they aſſuredly loſt. This was the firſt thing. But this is not all: In the next place, <hi>God</hi> committs into his hand a Rule, not <hi>heavenly</hi> Divine and ſpiritual, not the ſweet and candid Rule of Chriſt (whom they refuſed in his heavenly appearance,) but an <hi>Earthly Lordly</hi> Rule, puts an <hi>Iron Scepter,</hi> into his hand to daſh them in peices like a Potter's veſſel, and ſo anſwers theſe fools according to their folly, yet anſwers them not: Their ſpight was at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119024:14"/>the <hi>ſpiritual ſeed,</hi> therefore they ſhall have the Children of the <hi>Earthly Jeruſalem</hi> Reign over them (for theſe were his <hi>Body</hi> or his Princes which he ſet over all the Earth). Thus as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, or to entertain Chriſt in his meek large gentle heavenly appearance, which knows how to give <hi>men</hi> their Rights as well as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and every one their food in due ſeaſon; The Lord gives them up to their own hearts luſts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and feeds them with <hi>fleſh</hi> which they called for (a fleſhly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) till it came out of their Noſtrils, and they are ſick and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit again, and have enough of this Religious ſpirit, inſomuch that with all their hearts they would have had the power any where ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this hand, that, in the name of God and Religion, could do ſuch things, take away liberty and property, deſtroy their Rights, inſlave their perſons, alter and change laws and times at his pleaſure, break Oaths and Engagagements without remorſe. Any ſpirit but this ſpirit. Thus God filled them with their own ways, and puniſht them with their own Inventions. Thus he brought fire out of <hi>Abimelech</hi> to devour the men of <hi>Shechem:</hi> and fire out the men of <hi>Shechem</hi> to devour <hi>Abimelech,</hi> for they were a plague to each other, for they were of <hi>one ſpirit,</hi> but thus wonderfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be each others Torment.</p>
               <p>If you ask me now, What ſpirit this was that made ſuch work, what was the ſpirit of that Generation, and of Him that was in Judgment ſet over them (though in mercy too, I will grant you, for God did make uſe of him as a Bulwark, ſtill againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy, though we loſt ground within doors)? Was it an evil ſpirit how then could any good come from it? I anſwer, It was not a <hi>profane</hi> ſpirit, nor a ſpirit void of <hi>Religion;</hi> there was much of Religion and Righteouſneſs <hi>of one ſort</hi> in it: but if you would know what ſpirit it was, It was the ſpirit of the <hi>first Covenant,</hi> grafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed upon a new and living ſtock, Chriſt and the Goſpel, but bearing its own ſowre grape, The ſpirit of the <hi>Law</hi> (which you know makes nothing perfect) though in a <hi>Goſpel dreſſe;</hi> the ſpirit of the firſt born after the <hi>fleſh,</hi> or the life of Chriſt's <hi>first appearance,</hi> which is never ſafe and ſure from ſtarting back, &amp; returning to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, till it be made a ſacrifice ſeaſoned with <hi>ſalt,</hi> and ſalted with the <hi>fire</hi> of the eternal Spirit through the offering up of the fleſh. And becauſe this diſcovery is of ſo main importance, and concern unto
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119024:14"/>us, therefore I ſhall diſcourſe largely of it in the next Chapter, and ſhew you, How this is the Spirit in which our firſt life and Activity appears, and how it miniſters in the things of God (that is) in the <hi>firſt Court,</hi> and where it is to give up and reſigne; which when it doth not, it converts into <hi>Enmity</hi> againſt that better and latter ſpirit, and ſo is juſtly rejected and throwen off by God. And theſe things I ſhall, as God aſſiſts, diſcourſe to you not as <hi>Notions</hi> barely, but as things that have <hi>really</hi> operated and produced their fruits among us. Which if the Lord give us to underſtand and <hi>make</hi> a right uſe of, may make us wiſe to ſalvation to ſave our ſouls, (I am ſure), if not; to ſave the Nation, but, I ſay to ſave the Nation alſo, for <hi>This man ſhall be our peace</hi> when the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> ſhall come into the Land, and this wiſdome and knowledge ſhall be the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of our times: Though I cannot ſay whether we be yet hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and broken enough to receive it, but may put the Lord to caſt us again into the fire to make us <hi>Malleable</hi> to this Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Shewing what manner of Spirit that was, that miſcarryed in this Cauſe.</head>
               <p>I Am apt to believe that the Inſtruments which carryed on the work in this Nation generally were not miſtaken in themſelves, but that they were ſincere and upright with one ſort of upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and did indeed intend the freeing and delivering of us; yea, I am apt to retain that charity of the late <hi>Protector,</hi> that He inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no leſſe, when He diſſolved the <hi>long Parliament,</hi> and did thoſe High Arbitrary things: But it is not every ſpirit; Nay, it is not any ſpirit, be it never ſo raiſed and anointed, that can carry through to the end, in caſe of <hi>ſome temptations;</hi> but that ſpirit, that is by extraction <hi>divine.</hi> That that is of the Earth will ſeek, and at laſt find, its Center in the Earth, though it may by ſtrong <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines</hi> be carryed and kept aloft awhile: But natural principles, let them be never ſo much heightened, will never hold out to the end
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119024:15"/>of God's Works. As the eye of the <hi>fleſhly Iſraelite,</hi> could not ſee to the <hi>End</hi> of thoſe things that were to be Aboliſhed. And this is the great witneſſe which God is minding to hold forth unto us in this day, by all our Apoſtacy, and backſlidings, even to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>ſeed</hi> and <hi>ſeed, Spirit</hi> and <hi>Spirit. Then</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>ye ſhall returne and diſcern between the Righteous and the Wicked, &amp;c.</hi> There is a Righteouſneſſe in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> which is Wickedneſſe before <hi>God,</hi> not ſimply in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> but as it <hi>exalts,</hi> and magnifies it ſelf in a ſenſe of its own <hi>ſelf-ſufficiency,</hi> and in the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>its</hi> work, <hi>oppoſing</hi> the work and way that is <hi>more excellent,</hi> becauſe it finds not <hi>its own</hi> ſtrength, <hi>adaequate</hi> to it, as being that which <hi>Fleſh and Blood</hi> cannot endure, and yet cannot give way to <hi>Another,</hi> no not to the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf, by the breaking and crucifying it in its <hi>Natural</hi> abilityes, to do that which <hi>it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> do. This was the very Caſe in our Saviour's time. The Jewes were pitifully at a loſſe, and would faine have recovered their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſplendor, and glory; but they miſtook both their <hi>objest</hi> and their <hi>way</hi> to it, expecting a Carnal when the deſigne of God was a Spirituall Kingdome, and expecting to attain that by their own Righteouſneſſe, which God, diſcerning the inſufficiency and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Law</hi> to aſſiſt them unto, through the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> ſent his <hi>own Son</hi> to do for them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. And this is that alone that can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle and reſolve our Caſe. Therefore I ſaid, We muſt go into the Sanctuary to underſtand it.</p>
               <p>To clear this up (to thoſe that are ſpirituall and can judge what I ſay) I ſhall deſire to make this Queſtion, Whether this Apoſtacy that is upon us be not a <hi>Judgment;</hi> That is whether to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to ſuch a <hi>Reprobate</hi> ſenſe, as we ſeeme to be (both Rulers and people,) The one to <hi>act,</hi> and the other to <hi>accept</hi> and <hi>ſubmit</hi> to thoſe very things which we <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> be not a judgment from God upon us. For my part, I take it to be one of the greateſt of judgments, and an effect, and token of Gods forſaking, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring againſt a people; <hi>Spirituall</hi> Judgments are the greateſt of claring againſt a people; <hi>Spirituall</hi> Judgments are the greateſt of Judgments, for thus the wrath of God was revealed from Heaven againſt the Heathen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. for Corrupting themſelves in their known light, and not improving and going forward in it. Now whether the manifeſt tokens of ſuch a Judgment be not upon us; let every ſober mind conſider; And if ſo, If this Corrupting our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119024:15"/>ſelves be a Judgment, then neceſſarily through the righteouſneſſe of God, it muſt be the fruite and puniſhment of ſome preceeding ſin; either ſinfull <hi>Acts,</hi> or a ſinfull <hi>State,</hi> one or both, and ſo we ſhall come home to the point, to ſee what many of the adherents to this cauſe were, and how unlikely it was they ſhould bring forth any better fruit then as they have done.</p>
               <p>And in this diſquiſition we ſhall be upon ſurer ground in charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſinfull <hi>State</hi> which is generall (and which we muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, as being undeniably witneſſed, both by Scripture and all experience) then the particular <hi>Actions</hi> that turn'd them out of the way, which lye more dark, and are more immediately reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Judgment of God, though we are not altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light to gueſſe at them too. And firſt we muſt premiſe that of the Apoſtle. That is not firſt which is ſpirituall, but that which is Naturall. The firſt man is of the Earth earthly, the ſecond man is the Lord from Heaven. As is the Earthly, ſo are they that are Earthly, and as is the Heavenly, ſo are they that are Heavenly, and as we have borne the Image of the Earthly, ſo we ſhall beare the Image of the Heavenly. For fleſh and blood doth not inherit the Kingdome of God, neither doth corruption inherit incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is a Scripture that was wont to be read at the burial of the dead. We are now, I hope, burying this dead, the old man, and O that we might lay him downe in the grave of Chriſt, never to riſe in Corruption, or in a Corruptible and weake ſtate more! But to the Text. As God in bringing forth things out of the firſt <hi>Chaos,</hi> firſt ſets up man in a <hi>Natural</hi> Image, which was but the <hi>figure</hi> of the true, ſo in reſtoring things from the Chaos of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereinto they are fallen, he firſt brings forth man in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of a Naturall righteous life, and principle, which hath its beauty and Comelineſſe, though it be but as a <hi>flower,</hi> and ſoon withers if it be left <hi>alont.</hi> Yet God is not wanting to it, in ſerving it, with all advantages that it deſires of him, for the attayning of its end; and therefore according to his Covenant is juſt unto it, affording his preſence and bleſſing, untill it turnes off from him into its own crooked wayes: For though it be ſhort, and too weak to anſwer the Call and expectation of God in it ſelf, and God reſtifies ſo much unto it, and therefore calls unto it, to reſigne its life, and ſelf activity, and to take it up anew in him by another
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119024:16"/>Covenant; yet untill it refuſe this teſtimony, &amp; betake it ſelf proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perverſly to its own wayes, he doth not pronounce Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it, not totally deſert it. Now in the life and vigour of theſe firſt principles, did many, and thoſe not meane ones, ſet forth in our cauſe at firſt, which were but <hi>Gentile</hi>-principles, or principles common with the Nations, though mixt with better things (a light of Scripture and Propheſies at leaſt in the Letter) and theſe managed by men called up by the Spirit of the Nation which is a mixt Spirit; and perſons choſen, having a mixture of Spirit in themſelves at beſt, and what was of a purer and higher Nature was <hi>under,</hi> not <hi>above,</hi> was fain to <hi>ſerve,</hi> and to come as <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Eſaus</hi> Garments. When I ſay, it was but the ſtrength and vigour of a Naturall righteouſneſſe that girded moſt in their firſt ſetting forth; my meaning is not, to deveſt them of zeal to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Reformation. I can beare them record with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, they had (many of them) a zeal of God that way, and if that be more then Gentiles, we will admitt them Jewes, the people of God in Covenant with him. But what will that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, if there be a <hi>reſting in the Law,</hi> in things that may be ſhaken; if there be onely a forme of knowledge, and of the truth in the Law? Moſt of the Jewes had no more, and moſt profeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity are not beyond that; and yet I believe they are many of them in very <hi>good Earneſt,</hi> their hearts ſeem to be in what they profeſſe, but the very heart of the wicked (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) is little worth. The heart is deceitfull: The inward and trueſt life of the Naturall man, is but a <hi>form,</hi> a figure of life. <hi>Adam</hi> was no more in his beſt and pureſt ſtate. Therefore true Circumciſion is that of the <hi>Heart in the Spirit;</hi> not of the heart barely, but the heart in the Spirit. There is one, greater then the Heart, knowes all things (ſaith <hi>John.</hi>) The heart may lye, therefore (ſaith the Apoſtle) my Conſcience beares me witneſſe <hi>in the Holy-Ghost,</hi> that indeed is ſomething: elſe, Conſcience it ſelf is deceitfull where the Spirit hath not been at work, cutting down Man in his Naturall abilityes, and his own ſelf-exalting Righteouſneſſe. All his Religion may waſte and wither away. It cannot hold out againſt all batteryes and aſſaults that may be made. He that ſhall deſire a fuller witneſſe to this truth, let him peruſe Sr. <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> book, intituled; <hi>The Retired mans Meditations,</hi> where he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119024:16"/>ſhall find an ample teſtimony. This Honour muſt be given him (for God hath given it him) to be the firſt that in that clearneſſe hath miniſtred this knowledge to the world, ſince the night of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy fell upon it; wherein certainly he hath been ſpecially guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Holy Spirit. I can ſet my ſeale to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A Confirmation of the former, with the Hiſtorical Exemplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Principles in the late Tranſactions.</head>
               <p>SO then there was in our firſt Engagement, the ſhooting forth of ſuch a Spirit as God was pleaſ'd to entertain a <hi>Tryal</hi> of, and to joyne iſſue with, as far as it would goe in his work; And many of thoſe worthy <hi>Patriots</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> were, no doubt, accepted of God in their day, and were gathered home; where they are reaping the wages of their faithfull ſervices, being taken from the Evils to come, the time being not then for the two ſeeds and principles which were in this Cauſe, to be diſcovered in their diſtinction, or oppoſition rather, and to part aſunder; but being complicated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether (as light and darkneſſe, day and night, were in the firſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation before God divided them): the good ſeed was the bleſſing of the <hi>Cluster;</hi> though, I ſay, it was the younger Brother, and the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derling,</hi> and the other had the leading forth and management of all.</p>
               <p>But when that Spirit had done its work, and gone as far as it could goe, which was to cut downe that Spirit and work that was <hi>more unrighteous</hi> then it ſelf, wherein God owned them, and was aſſiſtant to them; then other work, of another, and far different, Nature appeared, unto which this Spirit that had acted ſo ſtrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and ſucceſsfully all this while, did bear <hi>no proportion,</hi> which yet was the end that God had, and ſtill hath in his eye, as the <hi>Crowne</hi> and advantage of all that <hi>Preparatory</hi> diſpenſation, which was frequently in the mouths of many, and they called it <hi>building work.</hi> How often was the late Protector (while General) heard to ſay, If ye have any more <hi>rough</hi> and <hi>breaking</hi> work for us to do,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119024:17"/>We are ready; but how to <hi>build</hi> or to lay one ſtone aright, we have no knowledge.</p>
               <p>Now was the time for <hi>faith</hi> to have been brought into exerciſe, and to have looked up for <hi>another</hi> Spirit, to take the work into its own hands, to have reſigned and given up to Him: which Spirit was amongſt us, and not improbably was diſcerned to be growing upon us: but men were afraid of it, and could not truſt themſelves with it, God ordering things ſo, that it appeared in much <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and unlikelineſſe of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and ſo was deſpiſed and rejected by the Builders. Many ſtumbling blocks alſo of <hi>strange</hi> Spirits and <hi>principles,</hi> being permitted to come forth with it: ſo that then had been the time for men to have thought ſeriouſly of that Commonition of our Saviour, <hi>Bleſſed is he that is not offended in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This work was the <hi>work of God,</hi> which he hath been carrying on through all ages even the <hi>ſetting up his Son</hi> upon his holy hill of <hi>Sion;</hi> This was that which God did but juſtly expect at our hands, That he having ſubdued all our enemies for us, and broken and put down all <hi>powers</hi> that ſtood in the way, we ſhould according to our many foregoing ſeeming promiſes and profeſſions, have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged theſe Nations to be his, and have given them up to be ruled and governed by him; and this Rule muſt have been given forth, and (when ever it appears, it ſhall proceed) out of <hi>Sion</hi> from the Lords own Spirit, in his poor broken <hi>Crucified</hi> ones, whoſe <hi>earthly</hi> wiſdom is brought into ſubjection by the Croſſe of Chriſt, to the <hi>Heavenly</hi> wiſdom which is <hi>fooliſhneſs</hi> with the world, whoſe weapons are not carnal but <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> mighty through <hi>God.</hi> The wiſdom that is from above, which is firſt pure, then peaceable, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, eaſy to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>But the Maſter-builders reject this corner-ſtone, and thinking ſcorn to deliver up the work to this Spirit, and to be out at any thing, though never ſo hard and difficult, having had the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an</hi> all this while, they could not fall in the <hi>Rear;</hi> having had the guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſhip of the Heir, they were loath to part with it, and to ſet up their <hi>younger Brother.</hi> Muſt our ſheaves bow to His? Therefore they take up a <hi>Manly</hi> reſolution, &amp; having ſome convictions upon them, of the right that Chriſt hath to the Kingdom's of this World,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119024:17"/>they could not down right deny him; and therefore in part ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting his title they are only ſollicitous to have as great a ſhare <hi>with him</hi> as may be; and therefore they will blunder upon the work as well as they may, and they will ſquare and model out the Government of Chriſt for him: and ſo they call a number of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons together of all ſorts of <hi>judgments</hi> and <hi>intereſts,</hi> which they choſe (with as much diſcretion as they had) of ſuch as were moſt likely to be friendly to this <hi>Mongrel Idea</hi> of a Kingdom, partly Chriſts and partly this Worlds. This ſo far as man can guels, was the very Conſtitution of the thoughts, and deſigns of the late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, in Calling the <hi>little Aſſembly,</hi> after the diſſolution of the Long Parliament, wherein he was upon this advantage, with many honeſt people: That he undertook this buſineſs not till ſuch time as the forementioned Spirit, and intereſt of Chriſt had been very much rejected, and hardly intreated by the Builders in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who had troubled ſome honeſt men, and threatned a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtorm upon tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p>What claim the Lord Jeſus did then lay to the Government of theſe Nations, in the very heart, and conſcience of the then Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor His <hi>Speech</hi> to that Aſſembly (ſome paſſages whereof have been ſince quoted by others) may teſtifie; and how it was entertained, the ſequel will ſhew.</p>
               <p>For though this Heterogeneous mixt Aſſembly, were not found of wiſdom, and moderation ſufficient to manage things, according to the Platform in the head of the Deſigners; yet they ſerved to give the Protector a colourable ground, and advantage to reject the thoughts of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> or the Rule of Saints, having now tryed them, and found ſuch an <hi>improportionateneſs</hi> in them to ſuch a work; which, ſome ſay, was that which was ſought and deſigned by him in the beginning. We need not be ſo uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſurmize that, it is enough and too much, that there was that ready and at hand, to lay hold on this advantage, to put Chriſt by the Throne as <hi>unfit</hi> to ſit there.</p>
               <p>And now, having taken this <hi>offence</hi> without any remorſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of mind, that generation of men turn their backs upon the the Kingdom of Chriſt, and uſurp the Grant of a <hi>longer Leaſe</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119024:18"/>for a Kingdom of <hi>this World:</hi> The Heir is an <hi>Idiot</hi> and He muſt have a <hi>Guardian,</hi> a Protector. Here was the firſt ſtone of <hi>Jericho</hi> laid again; Now did they ſet themſelves from that very day to build again the things they had deſtroyed: How far and how faſt the World recovered again after this, in the ſpace of five years, I think can hardly be paralell'd by the Declenſions of any time though ſome were to the laſt ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Of which number the Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be one.</note> fooliſh as to hope the Protector did but put on a <hi>Diſguiſe</hi> in all theſe Complyances with worldly Intereſt, and that he would (when he ſaw his opportunity) throw off this Mantle and come forth in his own true Spirit, which was hoped was to exalt Jeſus Chriſt in the head of all.</p>
               <p>If therefore it be demanded why we did not lift up our voice <hi>ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and reſtify againſt this Apoſtacy in the <hi>life-time</hi> of his late High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? The Anſwer is ready, That with great longſuffering we did wait, hoping better things, looking ever when the <hi>Scene</hi> would <hi>change,</hi> eſpecially in every <hi>Criſis</hi> of Affairs, the Lord hiding theſe <hi>dark</hi> Counſels from many, untill the event and iſſue declared them of what ſort they were. But now God hath made them ſo manifeſt, that he that runs may read, and it is that which is due to his works to take notice of them, and to ſanctifie his Name (which is holy) in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But if the Kingdome of Chriſt was indeed at the door, and come to the birth, it ſhould not have gone back again. For when God will work, who can lett? therefore ſure that was not the time, and therefore we are guilty of no ſuch A poſtacy as you charge us, nor his late Highneſſe of turrning his back upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Kingdom of God was not onely at the Door and come to the Birth, but <hi>it is born into the World,</hi> and is among us though as a Kingdome of <hi>Patience:</hi> Know ye not what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid of himſelf and of his Kingdom? <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.25. It ſhall indeed come as <hi>irreſiſtably</hi> as the light and as <hi>generally,</hi> and it ſhall be as evident and conſpicuous as the light, but <hi>first must he ſuffer many things and be rejected of this Generation.</hi> It is no Argument that the time is not, becauſe men reject the Kingdom: The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath its time to ſuffer as well as triumph, to ſuffer before it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119024:18"/>triumph: The Son of Man muſt be betrayed before he be inthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but <hi>woe unto that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed,</hi> though it be the fulfilling of the <hi>Counſell</hi> of God: So the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt be rejected of <hi>this Generation,</hi> What Generation? why mark who put the Queſtion unto our Saviour, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. The <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> the ſtricteſt Sect of Religious perſons among the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Generation we have been deſcribing in the foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of God could not be rejected, if it did not make its appearance: All men court Chriſt at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> and court the Kingdom of God in the <hi>Notion,</hi> in the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of it, they do not reject it there; but when it comes, not coming in <hi>their way,</hi> with obſervation and outward ſhew, they reject: it coming, not in the <hi>wiſe,</hi> in the <hi>mighty,</hi> in the <hi>noble,</hi> in the <hi>learned;</hi> but Chriſt riding on an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> coming in <hi>Fiſhermen,</hi> in the <hi>people</hi> that knew not the <hi>Law,</hi> this was the Offence, and is the Offence at this day. I have heard with my ears, in the time of the little Aſſembly, ſome of that Aſſembly ſay (into whoſe hands perhaps this may come, I pray the Lord they may conſider it and repent, for they are now of another mind); That if they did not think and believe there were ſome <hi>better</hi> and <hi>greater</hi> thing at the bottom, in the deſign of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence calling them together, then meerly to go upon an outward <hi>ſettlement,</hi> they would not continue at that work a day longer; ſuch convictions and awakenings of the Kingdom of God, its being at hand, were upon ſome Spirits that do now ſteer another Courſe.</p>
               <p>But to return: To what uncomfortable and dangerous waies and policies this diſobedience did ſubject his late Highneſſe, is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to conſider, ſometimes to court this party, ſometimes that; now with the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> then with the <hi>Preſbyterians:</hi> Then, when they galled him, turn to his old friends, and ſpeak kindly to <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> living upon the wrack all his daies, which made him, in all probability, ſeek his peace in <hi>forreign</hi> deſigns, with the noiſe and reputation thereof to drown the noiſe of Conſcience at home, which was ſtill gnawing at the Root: Then Anti-Chriſt muſt be conquered, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> power that upholds him. Until at laſt theſe continuall ſtrivings and fightings within, brought him down into his Grave. The Lord knows, I mention not this to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119024:19"/>bring up a blot upon his Memory, nor to inſult over his Aſhes; He that ſhall do ſo conſiders not that He was ſet forth unto us as a Mirrour of humane frailty: (Therefore be not high minded, but fear) and that it was not his perſonall ambition, or other Evils, but our ſins, in <hi>aſſociation</hi> together, that both gave him up to that <hi>temptation,</hi> and us to that <hi>ſubjection,</hi> wherein certainly he was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually unhappy with us, to be the Perſon that ſhould take away that liberty that He had been imployed to purchaſe for us, and to have all this ruine befall us under his hand. As for his ſin, it is to God, but the uſe of theſe things is to us, and upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count do I repeat them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A farther and more full Character of that Spirit, in many great Pretenders, that knew not our Cauſe, nor indeed ſerved it, but ſerv'd themſelvs of it. And a witneſſe againſt them.</head>
               <p>BUt why do I ſpeak of <hi>the Cauſe of God,</hi> when moſt of us are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it, and <hi>far from righteouſneſſe,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks. The Cauſe of God is a <hi>divine</hi> thing, and, as the <hi>day of God,</hi> Who may <hi>abide</hi> it? Is it <hi>our eaſe,</hi> our peace, our liberty, <hi>our promotion,</hi> our pleaſures, our Intereſts? Nothing leſſe; The Cauſe of God is that which <hi>ſearches,</hi> and tryes, and <hi>burns up</hi> all theſe, is an enemy to all theſe in that <hi>carnall</hi> and dark way of underſtanding, poſſeſſing and injoying of them, which men imagine.</p>
               <p>The Cauſe of God is that indeed which hath <hi>health,</hi> pleaſure, <hi>deliverance,</hi> and ſalvation in it for <hi>every Creature,</hi> rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and truly advanced and <hi>ſubjected</hi> unto; but of all that we have done, God may juſtly ſay, Did ye it <hi>at all to Me?</hi> Did ye take away the Biſhops at all to me? No: ye did it to <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and ye have feaſted your ſelves with their <hi>fleſh,</hi> their lands, their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues; Yea, their <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> (ſo far as for ſhame ye may) ye do joyfully exerciſe over your Brethren: When ye took off the <hi>King's</hi> head, did ye do it at all to me? No: It was to your ſelves, that ye might be <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>ſupream</hi> your ſelves. And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119024:19"/>hath not the Event ſhewed it? When ye aboliſhed the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> did ye it at all to me? Are ye not mad to ſet it up again? So that, why do we inquire after particulars wherein we have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray? when we have gone aſtray from the womb, from our firſt birth and ſetting forth in this Cauſe, we have acted from a gentile principle, from <hi>ſelf preſervation,</hi> for ſelf ends and advantages, from <hi>ſtomach</hi> and revenge, becauſe we ſuffered and were <hi>eclipſed</hi> by the former powers: Now, the Wrath of man works not the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God (the Apoſtle tels us), we were never ſubjected to God in thoſe Rods that were upon us; we could not lay down our lives and take them up again as Chriſt; we fullfil'd our own luſt, and were ſet to ſave our own lives in all we did. This is far from the righteouſneſſe of God: And this may be infer'd, not only from the <hi>State</hi> we wrought in, which was dark, and <hi>legal,</hi> and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (as that of old <hi>Iſrael</hi>); but from thoſe Characters of <hi>wavering uneavenneſſe,</hi> and uncertainty which accompanied all our Actings. Hence we were <hi>for the King,</hi> and <hi>against the King;</hi> for <hi>treating,</hi> and then for <hi>breaking off;</hi> for <hi>carrying on</hi> the Cauſe, and now for <hi>carrying it back:</hi> thus bringing upon our ſelves all the blood that hath bin ſhed in the Land, both on the one ſide and one the other: whereas the righteouſneſſe of God is a <hi>ſteady</hi> thing, is not yea and nay, puls not down to ſet up the ſame again. The righteouſneſs of God judges things in their root and <hi>principle,</hi> be they in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, not in <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>appearance,</hi> diſliking the ſame thing in this perſon, and countenancing it in another. If ye deſire to ſee your ſin, This is thy ſin <hi>O England!</hi> All our thoughts, all our wayes, all our motions, all our imaginations have bin, are, will be found before the Righteous God in this Day of his clear Judgment, that is coming upon thee, evil, onely evil, and that continually: thou canſt not turn thee to any one of them, to find the <hi>leaſt</hi> comfort and ſatisfaction of a good and righteous working and operation in them, for <hi>How can an evil tree bring forth good fruit,</hi> or a bitter fountain ſend forth ſweet water? Thy fountain is <hi>bitter,</hi> thy root is <hi>rottenneſſe;</hi> This I muſt teſtifie againſt thee, from the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119024:20"/>
               <p>Not but that thou haſt done Gods work, and fullfil'd and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted his pleaſure upon Kings, Nobles, Biſhops, and all the ſlain and poyled of the Land: Thou haſt dreſſed the Lord's ſacrifice but thou haſt done it <hi>in thine own ſpirit,</hi> and ſo art no better then <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> then <hi>John,</hi> then <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> and art accountable for all that thou haſt done: And God hath now taken thee in the ſnare of thy own heart, and hath ſpread thy filthyneſſe (thy unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, thy ambition, thy partiality, thy hypocriſie) in the ſight of the Sun. Thou art returned with the Dog to the vomit, and with the Sow to the wallowing in the mire; Thou haſt corrupted thy ſelf, and art become abominable, <hi>Judah hath justified Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> Thy ſins are as Scarlet, they are of a double dye to the ſins of the former generation which God hath caſt out before thy face: Thou ſaweſt the Judgments of God on them, for the wayes of <hi>pride, unjuſtice, oppreſſion,</hi> which thou walkeſt in, and waſt the Rod in his hand, the Inſtrument of his vengeance upon them, ſhalt thou therefore eſcape?</p>
               <p>O! I dread to think what a ſad reckoning this Generation hath to make! I can ſee no glimpſe of Comfort for us in any promiſe; or prophecy, or example, or record in Scripture: (unleſſe God powre out a ſpirit of grace and ſupplication, a ſpirit of deep con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and humiliation upon us) but our Carcaſes muſt fall in the wilderneſſe as <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s did. <hi>Loruhamah</hi> and <hi>Loammi</hi> muſt be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon us, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be as <hi>Ethiopia</hi> and the bringing up of the <hi>Phliſtins</hi> from <hi>Caphtor,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> from <hi>Kir</hi> ſhall be of as ſacred memory, as our Victories and ſucceſſes; the ſucceſſes of the <hi>great Turk,</hi> as holy things, as all our deliverances. I ſay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God make us aſhamed not onely of <hi>our ſins,</hi> but of <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and of the ſpirit and root we have growen upon, and acted from in all this? I ſpeak not now to natural men, I know God judges every one by the light and law that they are under, but I ſpeak to the Saints of <hi>England,</hi> that would be thought and call'd ſo, many moral men have done bravely and faithfully, and thoſe that have corrupted in thoſe principles, having profeſt no higher, ſhall be judged no deeper. But you that ſay, Ye ſee, you that have diſcern'd and cryed up <hi>a Cauſe of God,</hi> not civil liberties onely <hi>as men,</hi> but a Cauſe of God in civil liberties all <hi>for God,</hi> for the glory of God, for the <hi>Kingdome of God;</hi> I ſay, you ſhall be judged out of your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119024:20"/>own mouths. Is this the Cauſe of God? Is this the Kingdome of God? You in the Council, you in the Army; Is this the Cauſe of God, now your turn is ſerved? Moral men ſhall onely be judged for their work, not proſecuting the Cauſe, but letting it fall, but you ſhall be judged for no better a ſpirit unleſs you judge your ſelves, I ſay, there is no hope for you, unleſſe a ſpirit of judgment and burning ariſe up within you, and cleanſe your blood and filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from you. And ye ſhall pay not onely for your ſpirit, but for that guilt alſo wherein ye are in Common with others for not proſecuting, but letting fall this Cauſe, when ſo far carryed on though <hi>darkly</hi> and <hi>blindly</hi> by you, and in the letter. For the ſame evil made you <hi>deſiſt,</hi> namely <hi>ſelf-Intereſt,</hi> that made you manage it in unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>For be it known unto you, The Cauſe of God is amongſt us, and ſhall go on, and is carrying on through all theſe dark Meanders and Intricacies, whilſt you ſleep on your down Pillows, and ſtretch your ſelves upon your beds of Ivory, and the next advance of it will be <hi>the routing of you;</hi> Except God awaken you to meet him <hi>by ſpeedy Repentance,</hi> God will glorifie himſelf in his Judgments <hi>on you,</hi> as upon the <hi>Cavaleirs</hi> before you. Therefore truſt not in vain Viſions, and cry not, The Temple of the Lord. Is there any truth, mercy, and juſtice, in the Land? Are not the neceſſities of the poor as great as ever? are not the oppreſſions as many? is not pride, luxury, and profanneſſe, as rife? are not the Courts of Juſtice as corrupt? Is not the ſpirit of God reſtrained and perſecured? Is Chriſt in the Throne? Will ye call this a Reformation that <hi>ye are made Kings and Princes?</hi> No! the Lord will not own it: This is <hi>your work,</hi> and <hi>your Cauſe,</hi> it is none of his; and God will make you know one day <hi>ye had power</hi> to have reformed theſe things, but uſed it not, forſooth, becauſe you would have offended <hi>this great man,</hi> and tother <hi>uſeful</hi> Intereſt; ye muſt have broak with a <hi>broken</hi> ſhatter'd World, which will not be able to afford you the leaſt ſhelter in the day when God ſhall viſit you.</p>
               <p>God will carry on his own Cauſe, if we had never a tongue in the Parliament to plead it, nor never a pen in the Nation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for is, but what will become of you I know not? How God will do it I know not, but <hi>by his own appearing,</hi> It is the day of His Power, the day of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that is to have its turn next,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119024:21"/>not Man's day but God's, not Man's ſpirit but God's, and whom He will uſe as his Inſtruments I know not: if any of this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, it muſt be by a <hi>Regeneration</hi> of them, new moulding, new framing, new ſpiriting, new principling of them. The new wine muſt have new bottles, but I ſee little towards any ſuch thing in any of you. Yet I believe God hath a remnant among you, whom He will lead on to farther things, but it will be <hi>with weeping and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,</hi> with great brokenneſſe of heart, and poverty of ſpirit, with ſelf-judging and ſelf-abhorring, and then what revenge will ye take of your ſelves? what reſtitution will ye make to the Nation? what right will ye do to all men, even to your enemies? Then will ye throw away your Idols of Gold and Silver to the Moles and to the Bats. Then the lofty looks ſhall be humbled, and the haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man ſhall be laid low, and the Lord alone exalted in that day.</p>
               <p>Till the Spirit be thus powred forth from on high, I look for no ſalvation to be wrought, but the people ſhall labour in the fire for very vanity: If it be not in this ſpirit, in vain is all the tugging of our friends in Parliament, though I would not diſcourage any honeſt and righteous ſpirit to be holding up the bucklers againſt oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſlavery upon an honeſt account. Yet I fear me; nay, I ſee, and I ſee with joy, that the day is gone down upon the head of man in his higheſt Activity wherein he boaſts himſelf. The Princes of <hi>Zoan</hi> are become fools through our laying too much ſtreſſe on them. It is another ſpirit that muſt bring ſalvation, a ſpirit that is true indeed, that was never falſe, a ſpirit that cannot lye nor deceive, that cannot be corrupted. A ſpirit that hath overcome the World. And I hope this ſpirit is taking the work into his own hand in this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119024:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Containing a brief Recapitulation of ſome principal Heads, and the Concluſion of the whole.</head>
               <p>TO ſum up all briefly, and clear up more diſtinctly what hath bin in general hinted; Whoſoever is able rightly to diſcern paſt affaires, will ſee there was a <hi>double Cauſe</hi> ſet on foot amongſt us, <hi>viz.</hi> the Cauſe of God, and the Cauſe of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which moſt have had ſome notion of, but few have <hi>adequate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> deſcribed or rightly <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> them, only have admitted the Intereſt of <hi>Spiritual</hi> as well as <hi>Civil</hi> liberties. But certainly, the Cauſe of God muſt needs be higher &amp; larger, of nearer concerr, &amp; of greater conſequence than the Cauſe of the Nation, though that be great; as the Soul is more noble than the body, and the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to be preferred before the Creature. The Cauſe of God, like the Heavens, waters with its dew, cheriſhes with its influence, embraces in its Arms and boſome, the <hi>Natural Rights</hi> and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men as its Earth and Spouſe, in a <hi>ſubſerviency</hi> and uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to the illuſtration of its own bounty and glory. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are independent on the Earth, not ſo the Earth on the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; The Cauſe of God needs not us, but we receive all our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and bleſſing from it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As there were two Cauſes, ſo there were <hi>two people</hi> or ſorts of men, that were drawn forth to ſerve them: ſome upon a Natural and Civil account, only having a juſt reſentment of the langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſtate, of their Civil and Natural Rights and Liberties: and others upon a higher account, as being ſenſible of the ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we were in, as to <hi>ſpirituall affairs,</hi> by the Eccleſiaſtical Taskmaſters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe 2 Cauſes and their Adherents went hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a joynt &amp; ſocious way: the cauſe of God &amp; the cauſe of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119024:22"/>Nation. The People of God were concerned in both Cauſes, and contributed to both: not only their <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>fortunes,</hi> as we call them in common, with the Nation; but, beſides and above them, their <hi>Faith,</hi> their <hi>Prayers</hi> their <hi>Comforts,</hi> their <hi>Experiences,</hi> all their Intereſt in God, and in the Promiſes, for the promoting of both; and this not only out of love to themſelves, and their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular concerns; but in love to the Nation, and in duty and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God; whereby the Cauſe of the Nation in ſome ſenſe became to them the Cauſe of God, though always the diſtinction and ſubordination preſerved.</p>
               <p>The Cauſe of God conſiſts of <hi>two parts</hi> the one <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> ſuch as is the object of the <hi>Natural</hi> Man's diſcerning, <hi>viz.</hi> Freedom from <hi>outward</hi> violence and perſecution, in the <hi>externall</hi> exerciſe of Religion, and the worſhip and <hi>ſervice</hi> of God: which becauſe of things that relate to God, may in a <hi>large</hi> ſenſe be called the Cauſe of God; but in reſpect of the <hi>Subjects</hi> of theſe <hi>Liberties,</hi> which are <hi>all Men,</hi> or every Nation of men, they are but <hi>Natural</hi> Rights, ſuch as <hi>every ſort</hi> of Men and <hi>Religions,</hi> whether <hi>true</hi> or <hi>falſe</hi> do challenge and expect; for every Nation will walk in the Name of their God. This part of the Cauſe of God, is but as the <hi>outward Court,</hi> which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> may come into and tread down, and is ſuch an Intereſt as may be playd faſt or looſe withall by the Owners, if they hold it only on the tearms of a <hi>Natural</hi> Right, according as its makes with, or againſt their <hi>Ruling worldly Intereſt,</hi> or Concerns: whether it be profit or honour, as hath been too too manifeſt in theſe days: which hath made ſo many go back from thoſe Principles in this kind, which once they abetted and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for.</p>
               <p>The other part of the Cauſe of God is wholly ſpiritual, and ſo inviſible to that Eye that is only natural, though ever ſo enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, even in the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Scripture it ſelf, and is expreſt by the Apoſtle to conſiſt in the deliverance of the <hi>whole Creation,</hi> from the bondage of <hi>Corruption,</hi> into the glorious liberty of the <hi>Children of God.</hi> It is the delivering <hi>up all to God,</hi> the ſubjecting of all to him, which is the true <hi>liberty</hi> of the creature; and this delivering up to God, is not to Him as the head of the <hi>first Creation,</hi> exerciſing his Rule by natural Light or Principles: but as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119024:22"/>the Head of the <hi>New Creation</hi> by Chriſt riſen from the dead, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing a <hi>far higher</hi> and better Rule in the <hi>New</hi> Creature; which though it have for its <hi>Subject Matter,</hi> the ſame things that are found in the Rule of the Natural or Moral Conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> All <hi>External</hi> righteouſneſs, <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>worſhip;</hi> yet it hath them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another account, that is, on other <hi>grounds,</hi> and to other <hi>ends;</hi> and over and beſides them, it ſubjects the <hi>Mind</hi> in all its operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in theſe, to the <hi>Law of the Spirit of Life</hi> which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whereby the Creature is brought forth in <hi>newneſs of operation</hi> with Chriſt: not ſeeking <hi>its own glory,</hi> but the glory of <hi>its Head:</hi> as Chriſt ſeeks the glory of his Father. And this true ſpiritual and glorious liberty, where it is brought forth in any ſoul, is ſuch an intereſt as cannot be <hi>diſpoſed</hi> of, or <hi>parted</hi> with by its poſſeſſor, or made to <hi>ſerve,</hi> but diſpoſes of all things in that ſoul to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lord; ſeeking alwaies to do the things that pleaſe Him, not being able to do any thing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth. Thus thoſe whom the Son makes free, are free indeed, and abide in the houſe <hi>for ever,</hi> and never prove falſe nor turn their backs upon God, or that that is his intereſt and glory; Every other Spirit is <hi>corruptible,</hi> and the Rule and Law of its walking is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and <hi>variable,</hi> may be turned this way or that way, as worldly Intereſt or advantage ſwayes; but though every man be a lyar, yet <hi>God</hi> is true and cannot deny <hi>himſelf:</hi> and ſo are they true that are thus born of him, and become one Spirit with him, by the ſpiritual ſlaying and crucifying of that life in them, which is <hi>ſubject to chax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and may be corrupted, bribed, and bought off from its Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
               <p>Had <hi>all</hi> that took upon them the defence of our Cauſe been of this Spirit, we ſhould never have had cauſe to have complained of the betraying and deſerting of it.</p>
               <p>But that there were <hi>ſome</hi> of this Spirit under all the <hi>ſeveral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of light and diſcerning in this Cauſe; I do verily believe, who were therefore accepted of God, and bleſſed in their Deed and in Chriſt, were the bleſſing of the <hi>whole,</hi> and are many of them at reſt, whither they arrived, ſome ſayling through the Sea of their own blood ſpilt in the <hi>High places</hi> of the field: others ſpent and wore out themſelves in <hi>Counſels</hi> leaving the Remnant of their deſpiſed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119024:23"/>and <hi>afflicted</hi> Brethren, to ſuffer the indignation of an Apoſtate world, and to be ſad ſpectators of the havock and ſhipwrack of a bleſſed Cauſe, ready to enter the Haven of its publick obtaining and triumph. While this Spirit was up in our Counſels and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, God never withdrew from them; for God was the <hi>Father</hi> of it, and it is his own <hi>Child,</hi> and he cannot deny himſelf to this Spirit which is become a fool in it ſelf, and ſeeks all its wiſdom and dirction from him: therefore he cannot, he may not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it, When in the management of the moſt outward Affairs <hi>viz.</hi> our Martial Affairs, the Army or thoſe that had the conduct thereof, own'd this Spirit; they never were without Counſel nor without Signal ownings, and teſtimonys of acceptance from God. When they ſaid, They knew not their way but from ſtep to ſtep, when they had done one thing they knew not what was next: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve: were they guided in ſo ſafe and ſucceſsful a path, the Promiſe being to the <hi>bliud,</hi> that have thus made themſelves blind for the Kingdom of Heavens ſake, (that have reſigned their way and the leading of them to the Lord) that The will lead the blind by a way that they knew not: He will make darkneſs light, crooked waies ſtreight, and not forſake them.</p>
               <p>But when ſome thought they had been children and fools <hi>long enough,</hi> and had a luſt to be wiſe, and ſaw, that unleſs they were ſo, God did not make haſt enough to give them that which it may be he would have given, nay, certainly will give his people in his own time (Rule and headſhip over the world, and that with a clear evidence and demonſtration in the Conſcience of the world it ſelf, of the indubitableneſſe of their right and title thereunto, and their fitneſs alone, ſeparate from all other men to exerciſe this domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on). But I ſay, they would have it in their own time, and by their own way would raviſh and uſurp the bleſſing: and I could wiſh it were but ſo as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, and that no worſe might come of it, though that was bad enough; He got the bleſſing with a preſent curſe, and a great deal of ſorrow; But here is the very ſplitting and looſing of our Cauſe (ſo far as in them was to expoſe it) but that indeed it cannot be loſt, being the Cauſe of God and the whole world is his, and the Earth and all things muſt give up their dead; Whoſoever and whatſoever hath ſwallowed it up, muſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119024:23"/>it again: That's the comfort of it, which therefore incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges me, to hope it may not be in vain to cloſe with a word of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to all that are faithful,</hi> whether in Parliament or Army, or abroad in the Nation, or in any of theſe three Nations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever theſe may find them, That they would not give up their hope, that they would not deſpond concerning our good Cauſe, <hi>Joſeph is yet alive,</hi> the Cauſe lives ſtill, though under many <hi>gaſhes</hi> and <hi>ſtabs;</hi> yet it is alive, being of an <hi>eternal</hi> nature, it cannot dye. The Cauſe of God, the right of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt cannot be extinguiſhed: Therefore I beſeech you, prepare your ſelves to ſerve it, contend vigorouſly for it: It will ſhew it ſelf to you, and that ſhortly I am perſwaded, and that not to ſuffer any more. Maintain it a while, it will be able to maintain you. I ſay, All you that are born of it, and born into it, that have ſuckt its milk, that are <hi>Natural</hi> to this Cauſe, and it natural to you, Go on to ſeek the peace and welfare of it, It will reward you all. Perhaps you may diſcern it, ſome of you in one light, ſome in another gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually differing, as you may read before, is allowed; Let that make no difference at all, among you. Some it may be are exerciſed in the rights of men, others in the rights of Chriſtians, ſome more in the <hi>Letter,</hi> others more in the Spirit: The more outward <hi>not oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> that to the inward work and Kingdom, God accepts of the <hi>one</hi> as well as of the <hi>other.</hi> All did not bring the <hi>ſame</hi> offering to the Tabernacle; but ſome <hi>Badgers skins,</hi> while others brought <hi>ſilk</hi> and <hi>gold, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>lower</hi> is in order to the <hi>higher,</hi> the outward to the inward, and is in ſome ſenſe the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the inward: Therefore I ſay, ye are all one womans children. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above which is free, ſtand faſt in your Liberties; If any of your Brethren be at preſent found in oppoſition, they will, they muſt be brought over to you, it cannot be avoided: and thoſe that ſeemed ſometime friends, but were not, but ſervants of Mammoni you have an eaſe and freedom by the removall of them: for they were but a clog unto you, and for them you have loſt, you ſhall have double come forth to you, even from whence you leaſt of all expected; yea, Nations ſhall flow in unto you. Be but true to God, you ſhall never want <hi>strength,</hi> if all the Armies in <hi>Heavou,</hi> and all the Intereſt of God in the <hi>Earth</hi> be able to carry
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119024:24"/>you out, you ſhall not fall, nor ſhall your Cauſe fall. Only be <hi>ſample,</hi> and be not <hi>too wiſe</hi> to look before hand, as thoſe whoſe way is in themſelves; but as he that was brought down to <hi>God's foot,</hi> (that righteous man) ſo be ye waiting truly upon him in a Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedneſs of mind, following him as his Providence opens the way to you: deſigning nothing of your ſelves, and you ſhall ſee God will ſhew you what to do, yea how you ſhall recover this Cauſe again; for All things are poſſible to him, and it <hi>lives to him</hi> now: and he will make good what you do, and his glory ſhall be your <hi>rereward,</hi> when He goes <hi>before</hi> you, and who dares fall upon that Rear. And all this pittiful poor dark, worldly ſtuff which hath been built upon that precious foundation which God hath layd in this Nation, in the <hi>hearts</hi> of his people, and in the <hi>works</hi> of his providence, ſhall crumble and moulder away like dirt, and melt like wax before the fire of this righteous Appearing and ariſing of God in his poor broken Remnant, <hi>Amen, Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore ſerve the Lord without <hi>ſollicitouſneſſe,</hi> for your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovr ſhall not be in vain: <hi>Believe, ſo ſhall ye be eſtabliſhed.</hi> The words are few, and the Counſel is ſhort; but heed it well, and lay it to heart; It is of greater Moment then ye may be preſently aware of. I will not ſay, Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhall be unfulfilled; but it may be, ye may find the Lord hath ſaid ſo. I think I may ſay, It is the Counſel of God unto you for your good, which firſt or laſt muſt and ſhall take place and that ere long too,</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119024:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
